<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<title>Steven Hicks</title>
	<link href="https://stevenhicks.me"/>
	<updated>2019-06-19T07:00:00-05:00</updated>
	<author>
		<name>Steven Hicks</name>
		<email>steven.j.hicks@gmail.com</email>
	</author>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Guidance For THE BIG REFACTOR</title>
		<link href="/blog/2019/06/guidance-for-the-big-refactor/"/>
		<updated>2019-06-19T07:00:00-05:00</updated>
		<id>/blog/2019/06/guidance-for-the-big-refactor/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Most refactoring resources are about specific actions you can take in your code. Extract method, Remove middle-man, ...the kinds of actions that are well-documented at &lt;a href=&quot;https://refactoring.com/catalog/&quot;&gt;refactoring.com/catalog/&lt;/a&gt;. Missing is more general guidance for undergoing &lt;strong&gt;THE BIG REFACTOR&lt;/strong&gt;. You know the one. The one you&#39;re dreading, but you know you&#39;ll need to eventually do. The one you have ideas for but can&#39;t figure out how to start. The one that will in the end pay off large amounts of technical debt, but will cost you large amounts of brain cycles along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m currently in the middle of one of these. I feel a bit like I&#39;m in the weeds right now, struggling to find open air. So, yeah - this article is as much for me as it is for you. But my situation prompted me to take a step back, and start thinking meta. As I struggle through my own &lt;strong&gt;BIG REFACTOR&lt;/strong&gt;, and think about the things that have gone well or poorly, I offer this handful of suggestions to you - brave soul who is about to enter &lt;strong&gt;THE BIG REFACTOR&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. Move things out of the way that don&#39;t belong&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First things first, make yourself a clean workspace. There are functions that exist in the code you&#39;ll be tackling that shouldn&#39;t be there. Utilities that don&#39;t have anything to do with the current object. Objects that are &lt;em&gt;related&lt;/em&gt; to the code you&#39;re changing, but can live on their own. Move these things away from the problem - extract them to a method or object somewhere else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2. Choose your replacement strategy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will you...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modify the existing code-path? This requires you to complete before you can commit. Depending on how &lt;strong&gt;BIG&lt;/strong&gt; this &lt;strong&gt;BIG REFACTOR&lt;/strong&gt; is, this can be problematic and stressful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a second code-path side-by-side? Things can get out of sync this way. You&#39;ll need to look for changes to the original before merging, or enforce changes be made in both code-paths. This &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; allow you to test side-by-side, which is nice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Incrementally introduce your new code, using &lt;a href=&quot;https://martinfowler.com/bliki/BranchByAbstraction.html&quot;&gt;branch-by-abstraction&lt;/a&gt;? I am adding this option to sound smart - I only learned about it while looking for some guidance today, and haven&#39;t figure out how to apply it in my current scenario. It sounds great, though!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t know what the right answer is, for me or for you. They all make sense, sometimes, and I don&#39;t have a good heuristic for identifying the right fit. I often regret the path I choose - I regret the path I initially chose for this &lt;strong&gt;BIG REFACTOR&lt;/strong&gt;. I doubt you&#39;d want to use my heuristic even if I had one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spend some time thinking about which of these paths best fits before you begin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3. Cover the system with tests&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not just any tests, the &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; tests. Not tests that test implementation of existing code - those will get deleted during your refactor, and won&#39;t tell you if you broke something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The right tests are at a higher level than what you&#39;re replacing/rewriting, and which don&#39;t care about the implementation you&#39;re writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They might be integration tests. They might be UI tests (I&#39;m totally digging &lt;a href=&quot;https://cypress.io&quot;&gt;Cypress&lt;/a&gt; for those right now). Possibly a controversial opinion on my part - they don&#39;t necessarily have to be &lt;em&gt;permanent&lt;/em&gt; tests - they can just be your guide for now, and you can delete them when you&#39;re done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cover &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; you&#39;ll be replacing with these tests. You&#39;ll use them along the way to test for regressions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;4. Focus on your health.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will get swallowed up by the problem. Don&#39;t let it take away the things you know you need to be healthy and happy. Don&#39;t lose sleep, don&#39;t skip meals, don&#39;t skip exercise. Treat it like a marathon, not a sprint. Pace yourself. You&#39;re not going to power through &lt;strong&gt;THE BIG REFACTOR&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take breaks. Let your mind wander and think about the problem on its own. Your brain will work on the problem without you forcing it to. It&#39;s called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Incubation_(psychology)&quot;&gt;incubation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;5. Document everything.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep a NOTES.md file in your codebase, right next to your changes, so everyone can see it. Keep track of...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Things you discover that you know you&#39;ll have to account for&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Things you think might help you solve problems along the way&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Issues you run into that you know you&#39;ll have to fix&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ideas of things you want to change - make a backlog, don&#39;t work on them all at once&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;6. Commit &amp;amp; get feedback frequently.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Committing frequently is not so hard. Finish each phase of your &lt;strong&gt;BIG REFACTOR&lt;/strong&gt; by committing the work and pushing it. This allows you to start each next phase with a clean slate; which makes it easier to revert when you get stuck in a corner or decide on a direction change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting feedback frequently is harder, at least for me. I like for my work to be reasonably polished before I submit it for feedback. I&#39;m trying to get better at this. As my coworker Chris told me today, he could have reassured me that I was on the right track with &lt;em&gt;half&lt;/em&gt; the work I&#39;d done so far. My emotional state &lt;em&gt;definitely&lt;/em&gt; could have used that encouragement a day or two ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feedback is especially hard with big problems, because you have the large problem space modeled in your head, and it&#39;s hard to share that with others. It can feel counterproductive to bring someone into your model - there&#39;s lots of explaining to do. Resist the temptation to drive forward on your own, though. Getting feedback will help you make sure you&#39;re on the right path, and give you ideas along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;7. Take baby steps.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Know generally where you&#39;re headed, but think about how you can get there in as small of steps as possible. Apply small refactoring actions, and commit them frequently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Address the biggest issues early if you can, or defer them if you aren&#39;t sure of the right abstraction for them. The right time will present itself for you to address them - don&#39;t force it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;8. Acknowledge that &lt;strong&gt;THE BIG REFACTOR&lt;/strong&gt; is hard work.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allow yourself to take time. Writing code that solves a new problem is easier than writing code that solves an old problem. When you&#39;re solving a new problem, you don&#39;t know very many edge cases, and you can approach with simpler abstractions. When you&#39;re solving an old problem, the edge cases are all known, and the right abstractions to cover them all take more thought and consideration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Good luck!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope your &lt;strong&gt;BIG REFACTOR&lt;/strong&gt; treats you well! Or at least, you pay off some debt with minimal scars. Let me know how it goes, and &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:steven.j.hicks@gmail.com&quot;&gt;send me an email&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pepopowitz&quot;&gt;hit me up on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; if you have advice that I didn&#39;t cover!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Building A Workshop</title>
		<link href="/blog/2019/02/building-a-workshop/"/>
		<updated>2019-02-19T06:00:00-06:00</updated>
		<id>/blog/2019/02/building-a-workshop/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Presenting a 45-minute session at a meetup or conference is really fun. I&#39;ve never thought that was enough time to do more than inspire people to research the topic. In 2018, I decided I wanted to get more out of speaking. I wanted to feel like I was &lt;em&gt;teaching&lt;/em&gt; people, in addition to inspiring them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I started leading workshops. I &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MusicCityTech/status/1002264602422456331&quot;&gt;led a half-day workshop at Music City Tech&lt;/a&gt; on writing Test-Driven JavaScript, and then &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pepopowitz/status/1049406551994306560&quot;&gt;a full-day workshop at Dev Up&lt;/a&gt; called &amp;quot;Building Your First React App&amp;quot;. In early 2019 I &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/anaccidentaldev/status/1082665637229531141&quot;&gt;led my React workshop again at CodeMash&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve definitely walked away from these first few feeling like I&#39;m teaching and making a difference. If workshops are something you&#39;ve considered, I encourage you to give them a shot. I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; most conferences get significantly less submissions for workshops than talks, so it is easier to get started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that&#39;s you, then you might be interested in some things I&#39;ve learned about building workshops in the past year!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;It takes a lot of time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A half-day workshop probably took me about 50 hours to put together; a full-day workshop took about 100 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s a lot of time! Before it scares you off, you should know these things for context:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It takes me about 40 hours of work to put together a one-hour talk. I obsess over the flow of a talk, I add drawings, and I script (effectively) every talk I write. This is more time than most people put into a talk. So 50/100 hours is likely on the high side of what it would take you to build a workshop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a very specific balance of talking-to-hands-on that I strive for. I don&#39;t like to talk for more than 20 minutes before people get their hands on their keyboard for 20 minutes. I think this forces me to put more time into thinking about how exercises can build from each other, and how I can break exercises down into smaller pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Think a lot about what kind of workshop you want&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer to this question probably has a big effect on how much time it takes to build your workshop. I&#39;ve seen a few different styles of workshop, each with advantages and disadvantages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The self-driven workshop&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some workshop leaders say a few words at the beginning, then let people dig in on their own for the rest of the 4 hours. I call this a &amp;quot;self-driven workshop.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The self-driven workshop is a favorite of attendees who want to work on their own time. They don&#39;t really need the leader there, so they can take the exercises home with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, this strategy gives learners more opportunity to distribute skill-wise. Fast learners will finish everything within an hour; slow learners will take more. Many learners will even leave when they realize it&#39;s completely self-driven, knowing they can work on it at their convenience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My preference is to engage with learners early and often - so I stay away from the self-driven workshop. If you batch your exercises small, you see less of a gap between the fast and slow learners. You might end up with a range of 10 to 20 minutes with small exercises, compared to 1 hour to 3.5 hours for a self-driven workshop. This is more likely to keep everyone engaged for the entire session, and it gives me more opportunities to interact with people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The lecture&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some workshop leaders can fill all 4 hours with instruction. They are deep experts in their field, and have tons of knowledge to share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not this level of expert. I also don&#39;t think 4 hours of lecture is engaging for an audience. Human attention span is short. You get maybe 20 minutes before people start to check out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a workshop, people have their laptops in front of them. If you give them an opportunity to check out, they will take it, and you will struggle to get them back. This doesn&#39;t mean they&#39;ll sit there and play minesweeper for the next 3 hours. It means they&#39;ll spend 20 minutes on Twitter, then decide &amp;quot;this sucks, I&#39;m not getting anything out of it&amp;quot;, then walk out to another session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It isn&#39;t only 100% talking that makes for a boring workshop. Even if you split your workshop into 1 hour talking then 3 hours of hands-on, that first hour is an opportunity for people to check out before you even get to the exercises. At the very least, I&#39;d consider breaking this balance into [30 minutes talking, 1:30 exercises, :30 talking, 1:30 exercises]. Even better would be 15 minutes talking/45 minutes exercise repeated 4 times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The interactive workshop&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No surprise I&#39;m sure, but this is definitely my preferred style of workshop. I strive for about 15 minutes of talking, then about 20-30 minutes of exercises of some sort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Variety of exercise is also important in this style of workshop. Repetitive exercises can get boring. My favorite workshops that I&#39;ve attended have used a variety of styles of exercise. A mix of hands-on coding, looking at code, pairing, just talking about things,… In my React workshop, I have learners draw components on handouts with a pen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running an interactive workshop requires strict time-boxing, to make sure you&#39;re covering all the things you want to cover. It is really easy to run over time on exercises. You&#39;re an expert in your field, and your audience is full of beginners - every exercise you write will take them longer than you think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is okay, they&#39;re learning! You just need to be okay with cutting an exercise short when you know time is up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Get people talking to each other within the first 20 minutes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re interested in leading a lecture or self-driven workshop, this is probably not necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agile coaches/speakers are especially great at making this happen. Even if it&#39;s a simple &amp;quot;meet your neighbor&amp;quot;, getting people talking early sets the tone of keeping people interactive and engaged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my workshops, I&#39;ve mostly only tried the &amp;quot;meet your neighbor&amp;quot;. I required pairing for one exercise in my Test-Driven workshop, but it didn&#39;t go great. It seems like a lot of people have resistance to pairing. I have a deep love for pairing. I think if done well it can be career-changing, so I still want to share that experience with people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ll back off on the pairing &lt;em&gt;requirement&lt;/em&gt; in the future, and make it &lt;em&gt;optional but encouraged&lt;/em&gt;. I also could better support pairing by taking time up front to say “if you want to pair, raise your hand right now…and find each other.” It would require people moving seats, but it might work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Written instructions are really helpful&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is &lt;strong&gt;incredibly&lt;/strong&gt; helpful to give your audience detailed instructions for exercises. Anything less will leave them lost and confused. Don&#39;t assume anything is understood that you haven&#39;t already explained. Provide links to resources for things that you didn&#39;t explain. The more details you give them, the fewer questions you&#39;ll have to answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s even helpful to include basic information that you &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; cover in your lecture/instruction. Some people might not have understood it when you were speaking. Others might do better with reading than listening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even the exercises where laptops aren&#39;t used should have written instructions. Once your learners are conditioned to look at your written instructions for each exercise, they will look there even when there aren&#39;t any.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Post the instructions in a public location&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn&#39;t a requirement, but attendees are really appreciative when they can (a) finish the exercises on their own, and (b) share them with their coworkers. I put all of mine &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pepopowitz/your-first-react-app-exercises&quot;&gt;in a GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Enable people to jump into later exercises easily&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very few people will complete every exercise in a workshop, from start to finish. Some might join your session halfway through. Some might get stuck on an exercise, and since &lt;a href=&quot;#the-interactive-workshop&quot;&gt;you&#39;re strictly time-boxing&lt;/a&gt;, they might not have time to finish it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To account for this, build your exercises in a way that someone can jump into a later one without having finished everything before it. This will help them focus on the current exercise, and it will free you up from solving issues from 3 exercises ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I accomplished this &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pepopowitz/your-first-react-app-exercises&quot;&gt;in my React workshop&lt;/a&gt; by having each exercise start with the &amp;quot;completed&amp;quot; state of the previous. I have a separate folder for each exercise, and all the code for all exercises is readily available. I give them the starting point for each exercise, and a folder containing the completed state in case they get stuck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve also seen people accomplish this with git branches, commits, or tags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Finding the right difficulty level is...difficult&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s important to me to have a difficulty level that (a) isn&#39;t too hard for brand new beginners, but (b) doesn&#39;t bore the advanced learners. This is a really hard balance to find.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way I first approached it, with my TDD workshop, was to try to make the exercises &lt;em&gt;so long&lt;/em&gt; that no one would ever finish. I thought this would keep the advanced learners interested, without the beginners having to worry about how far they got.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach definitely appeased the advanced learners, but it had a damaging effect on the beginners. They became stressed out that they were never able to finish. Several people commented on how far behind they felt after my workshop. This felt awful - I &lt;strong&gt;never&lt;/strong&gt; want to make beginners feel that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that knowledge in hand, I did a better job of planning exercises in my React workshop. I aimed for activities that would take &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt; about 5 minutes to complete. Because I have significantly more experience in the topic, this ends up being &lt;strong&gt;plenty&lt;/strong&gt; of work for the advanced learners without overwhelming the beginners. Just in case an advanced student finished work quickly, I threw in a link to an interesting related article and/or a vague &amp;quot;bonus&amp;quot; exercise that could keep them busy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will get a wide range of experience levels in your workshop. It’s up to you to decide what you want to do with those people. Do you want to teach to the least experienced person in the room, at the risk of someone more advanced walking out? Are you more interested in keeping the advanced students happy at the risk of frustrating the beginners? I aim for the middle, and expect to lose a few people on either end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Be flexible with time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Give people breaks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I knew going into my first workshop that I needed to account for breaks. &lt;em&gt;No one&lt;/em&gt; can sit for 4 hours, no matter how funny my dumb jokes are. I scheduled one break into my Test-Driven workshop, about halfway through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We didn&#39;t get anywhere near halfway before we needed it. I could see the lack of focus in their eyes. We took our break earlier than expected, and then a second a little over an hour later. My schedule was a little messed up, but we recovered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I factor in two breaks per 4 hour session, about ten minutes for each break. I don&#39;t schedule them, though. I find it more effective to gauge the temperature of the room when we&#39;ve been sitting for an hour. I start looking ahead at my schedule (which is conveniently broken down into 15-20 minute chunks), to figure out when our next break will fit in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Let them choose the last topics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s hard to stick to an exact schedule for a workshop. Embrace this by over-planning topics. Plan out a couple more than needed to fill the session, but let your group choose which topics they&#39;re most interested in at the end. They&#39;ll appreciate having control over the curriculum, they&#39;ll get more out of your session, and you&#39;ll feel like you&#39;ve tailored your course for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Watch out for logical leaps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m still learning this lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s easy, as an expert in your topic, to make logical leaps. In my React workshop, we talk about &lt;code&gt;setState&lt;/code&gt; for managing component state. The next logical concept to me is application-level state. But there is a big difference between managing component state and managing application state. It took me months of experience to understand the nuances and differences between the two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s hard to boil that experience down into 15 minutes of lecture. It&#39;s a big leap for someone who just learned about component state to understand &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; application state is, &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; it&#39;s different from component state, &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; it matters, and &lt;em&gt;OMG this doesn&#39;t look anything like component state&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is definitely your responsibility to figure out how to guide them through these leaps. But it&#39;s also easy to underestimate the size of those leaps. Err on the side of caution. Always assume the leap is bigger than you think it is, and never assume they&#39;ll be able to make the leap without a lot of assistance from you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I look back at this tweet often, as a reminder of how slowly I should be transitioning through concepts while teaching:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Sometimes I read things on edutwitter from someone who thinks they have discovered something amazing, which often sounds profoundy, thinky, or researchy, and I sigh and reflect on how music educators have known said thing for years. In evidence I give you Mrs Curwen, 1886: &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/fvPgXVJUL9&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/fvPgXVJUL9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Martin Fautley (@DrFautley) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DrFautley/status/1024227769004306432?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;July 31, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Focus on the learners&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It feels nice to have a room of people looking to you for guidance. Just remember that the workshop is not about you, or your ego, or all the things that you know - it&#39;s about the awesome people who came to learn from you. Do everything in your power to make learning easier for them.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>2018 In Review</title>
		<link href="/blog/2019/01/2018-in-review/"/>
		<updated>2019-01-29T06:00:00-06:00</updated>
		<id>/blog/2019/01/2018-in-review/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;2018&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A year is a long time. What you feel about yourself today is most certainly different than what you felt about yourself one year ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They say that the most important parts of a talk/lecture/presentation are the very beginning, where you hook them...and the very end, which is what they remember. The same could be said for a year. You could do 100 amazing things in the first nine months, but if the last three months stunk? You&#39;d think you had an awful year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That explains why I had a hard time remembering what I was most proud of when I looked back at my 2018 in December.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;I&amp;#39;m feeling in a bit of a slump right now, and it took me way longer to think of these than I would have liked. I&amp;#39;m hoping to get better at celebrating (&amp;amp; remembering) my victories this year. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And also, to get better at focusing on the practice, not the outcome.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Steven Hicks (@pepopowitz) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pepopowitz/status/1078291468102586368?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;December 27, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took a look back at my Twitter feed from 2018, though, and things looked pretty dang good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;I Did More Speaking Than Expected!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heading into 2018, I thought that I was going to have to cut back on speaking. My job wasn&#39;t happy about me taking time &amp;quot;off&amp;quot; to speak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I still managed to present 12 times! This is as many times as I presented in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took a few vacation days to do it, which I wasn&#39;t thrilled about. I also had some help from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/oobert&quot;&gt;my friend Tony&lt;/a&gt; advocating for me at work, convincing people that I was helping the company. I also did a good amount of local speaking - 5 times out of 12, to be precise. This breakdown also mirrored my 2017 speaking engagements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;At CodeMash&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My speaking year started off with a trip to Ohio for CodeMash, a conference I&#39;d heard a lot of things about. My talk went great, but my highlight was giving a lightning talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one of the pre-compilers, we learned how to use a Recurrent Neural Network (RNN) to take a bunch of samples of text, and generate similar samples. It turns out there is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kaggle.com/rounakbanik/ted-talks&quot;&gt;huge collection of TED Talk transcripts available&lt;/a&gt; - I used them to generate a new TED Talk, which I then presented at the CodeMash lightning talks....as a TED Talk. It was super fun!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/CodeMash?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#CodeMash&lt;/a&gt; Lightning Talks happening now! &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pepopowitz?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@pepopowitz&lt;/a&gt; giving a machine learning-generated TED Talk &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/IBtvjnl7lr&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/IBtvjnl7lr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; John M. Wright (@Wright2Tweet) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Wright2Tweet/status/951251467675029504?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;January 11, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;.&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jennifermarsman?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@jennifermarsman&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Saelia?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@Saelia&lt;/a&gt; did a great workshop yesterday, on using neural networks to turn existing bodies of text into new ones.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And thus, I find myself preparing a lightning talk in which I present a fake TED talk, generated from existing TED talks, as a TED talk. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/codemash?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#codemash&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/1Fw3bzNgUZ&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/1Fw3bzNgUZ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Steven Hicks (@pepopowitz) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pepopowitz/status/951122404088131584?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;January 10, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qpeq-4dFVvg&quot;&gt;listen to the talk on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;At Open Source North&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open Source North is one of my favorite conferences to speak at. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jeffurban&quot;&gt;Jeff Urban&lt;/a&gt; puts together a great conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The venue is also great:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;I repeat my request from last year - if every conference could just install a Japanese garden for pre-game relaxation, that&amp;#39;d be great.&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/osn2018?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#osn2018&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/H0q69BTB8Y&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/H0q69BTB8Y&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Steven Hicks (@pepopowitz) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pepopowitz/status/1007266869013831681?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;June 14, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a great time here, and a lot of people joined me to talk about React testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Packed room for &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pepopowitz?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@pepopowitz&lt;/a&gt; dropping knowledge bombs with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/fbjest?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@fbjest&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Airbnb?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@Airbnb&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Enzyme?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#Enzyme&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;.&lt;br&gt;.&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/OpenSourceNorth?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@OpenSourceNorth&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/OSN2018?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#OSN2018&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/DeveloperCommunity?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#DeveloperCommunity&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/zBjr7BpAi1&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/zBjr7BpAi1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Chris DeMars (@saltnburnem) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/saltnburnem/status/1007295805445890049?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;June 14, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10/10 would do again....though I can&#39;t submit this year, due to it being held on my partner&#39;s birthday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;At That Conference&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thatconference.com&quot;&gt;That Conference&lt;/a&gt; is a special event to me - the first conference I attended, and the place I caught the speaking bug. I was thrilled to speak for the second time here. Even more thrilled when one of my speaker heroes, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/housecor&quot;&gt;Cory House&lt;/a&gt;, walked into the room halfway into my talk. If you watch &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-JeyIdKPNsE&amp;amp;t=39m55s&quot;&gt;the video&lt;/a&gt;, you can hear me say &amp;quot;Hi, Cory!&amp;quot; because I am a total spaz and got excited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Solid React testing advice from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pepopowitz?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@pepopowitz&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/ThatConference?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#ThatConference&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;1. Consider extracting complex logic to plain JS utility functions. &lt;br&gt;2. Minimize common setup so it’s easy to see what makes each test unique.&lt;br&gt;3. Use enzyme-to-json for shorter snapshots&lt;br&gt;4. Optimize for fixing tests &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/jRJd0np2vI&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/jRJd0np2vI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Cory House 🏠 (@housecor) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/housecor/status/1026867353185861632?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;August 7, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;In A Hot Dog Costume&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the fall, I spoke for the first time at the Milwaukee JS meetup. Because it was halloween, and because I have a children&#39;s hot dog costume in my closet that I haven&#39;t gotten enough value out of, I talked about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.11ty.io&quot;&gt;EleventyJS&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://netlify.com&quot;&gt;Netlify&lt;/a&gt; while in a children&#39;s hot dog costume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;We are the only place in &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/mketech?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#mketech&lt;/a&gt; where a hotdog gives the presentation. At least, we are pretty sure. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/zzb3xeHVfh&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/zzb3xeHVfh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Milwaukee JavaScript (@mkejs) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mkejs/status/1057413941536714752?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;October 30, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/dfAmGqgINb&quot;&gt;watch a recording of this talk&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried something in this talk that I don&#39;t usually do, and that I usually caution people to avoid - live demos. It felt like the right conditions for demos. I knew the subject very well, and I thought the meetup audience would want more than slides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not sure if it was the right decision. At the very least, I would not do demos while wearing a hot dog costume again. I spent a lot of time moving the costume out of my face while typing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also literally put someone to sleep in this talk. It was night-time and he was older, but I also just went way too long. But I&#39;m one of the few people who can say I&#39;ve done live demos while in a hot dog costume!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;I Started Recording My Talks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my &amp;quot;goals&amp;quot; (what even are goals?) is to speak at an international conference. I&#39;d heard from several people that many larger/international conferences won&#39;t even consider you without a video. I&#39;ve not spoken at a conference that recorded my talk, so I took it upon myself and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-JeyIdKPNsE&quot;&gt;started&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KxqKZHg7RWU&quot;&gt;recording&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bmNuOsD0zF0&quot;&gt;my talks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inspired by advice from &lt;a href=&quot;https://jeremybytes.blogspot.com/2016/09/recording-live-presentations.html&quot;&gt;Jeremy Clark&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://digitaldrummerj.me/recording-my-conference-talks/&quot;&gt;Justin James&lt;/a&gt;, I decided the video mattered less than the audio. I bought a cheap-ish action camera (GoPro Hero Session); it&#39;s fine. It records video! But not great video. It lasts long enough on one charge to do slightly more than one hour-long session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I traded a bike trailer with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ivaneisenberg&quot;&gt;Ivan Eisenberg&lt;/a&gt; for a Zoom recorder. It is much better than the camera. I wear two microphones when I&#39;m presenting, to get good recorded sound, but no one makes fun of me. (At least not to my face.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not great at editing. Correction - I&#39;m not even mediocre. It&#39;s hard to get good at something when you do it about 4 times a year. But hey, people can see that I don&#39;t throw up on myself when I speak, and that&#39;s all that matters. I think?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;I Did Less Writing Than I&#39;d Hoped&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was secretly hoping to write about one article a month in 2018. I ended up with less than half that. I spent &lt;strong&gt;a lot&lt;/strong&gt; of time working on talks/workshops, and it prevented me from writing more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I shared a few of my articles on Medium. &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@pepopowitz/chekhovs-gun-and-better-unit-tests-96fb439e6d0e&quot;&gt;I wrote about what we can learn about unit testing from a Russian playwright&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@pepopowitz/10-tips-for-writing-conference-talks-20d958bf3f51&quot;&gt;I shared some tips for writing a conference talk&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@pepopowitz/5-tips-for-writing-a-conference-submission-ebd41ae9a961&quot;&gt;I offered advice on submitting an idea to a conference&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;But I Got Paid To Write!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve kicked around the idea of getting into developer relations for a while. One thing I&#39;ve never been sure about is being paid to write/speak about a specific product, instead of &amp;quot;whatever I want.&amp;quot; This feels like a situation where I&#39;d have trouble motivating myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got an opportunity to find out, when &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/flydotio&quot;&gt;Fly&lt;/a&gt; accepted my proposal to &lt;a href=&quot;https://fly.io/articles/adding-another-layer-to-the-stack/&quot;&gt;write an article for them&lt;/a&gt;. They have a great team. They were really helpful getting me up to speed with Fly Edge Apps, and they helped me craft an idea and a solid article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I came away from the experience feeling like I could definitely write/speak for a living, especially if I believed in the product. I&#39;m still worried about the amount of travel that a dev advocate does. That just isn&#39;t realistic for me right now. But maybe this type of role is in my future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;I Was On A Podcast! Twice!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early in 2018, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/davidpine7&quot;&gt;David Pine&lt;/a&gt; connected me with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/raelyard&quot;&gt;Dave Rael&lt;/a&gt;, and I got to be a guest on the Developer On Fire podcast! I had a great time &lt;a href=&quot;https://developeronfire.com/podcast/episode-317-steven-hicks-scary-things&quot;&gt;talking to Dave about &amp;quot;doing scary things&amp;quot;, becoming a speaker, and tightening your feedback loops&lt;/a&gt;. And the movie &amp;quot;Medicine Man&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In early summer, while at &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MusicCityTech&quot;&gt;Music City Tech&lt;/a&gt; in Nashville, I got a chance to record another podcast - this time with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mgroves&quot;&gt;Matt Groves&lt;/a&gt;, on the Cross-Cutting Concerns podcast. &lt;a href=&quot;https://crosscuttingconcerns.com/Podcast-089-Steve-Hicks-Speaking&quot;&gt;We talked about the differences between writing an hour long talk and building a half-day workshop&lt;/a&gt;. Spoiler: there are differences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;My Scary Thing Was Workshops!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time last year, I was trying to decide what my &amp;quot;scary thing&amp;quot; was going to be in 2018. I had some candidates, but I wasn&#39;t really sure where I wanted to invest my time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I was at CodeMash 2018, I bounced in between the workshops, taking notes on what seemed to work well and what didn&#39;t. By spring, I decided that leading workshops was where I wanted to put my energy for 2018. I started submitting workshop ideas to conferences. I was lucky enough to have ideas accepted twice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Music City Tech&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In late May, at Music City Tech in Nashville, I led a workshop called &amp;quot;Building Quality JavaScript With Test-Driven Development&amp;quot;. It was 4 hours long, and took &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of time to build. It went pretty well, but I definitely learned a few things about keeping people engaged &amp;amp; energized. I needed to take more breaks than I thought. My exercises were too long &amp;amp; too difficult. In one case, I made too large of a leap from one exercise to the next, and didn&#39;t give enough background or context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Building Quality JavaScript with Test-Driven Development&amp;quot; with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pepopowitz?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@pepopowitz&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/WIuXiW9wz9&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/WIuXiW9wz9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Music City Tech (@MusicCityTech) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MusicCityTech/status/1002264602422456331?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 31, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Dev Up&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October, I led a workshop called &amp;quot;Building Your First React App&amp;quot; at the dev Up Conference in St. Louis. This went really well! I applied a lot of my learnings from my first workshop. Smaller exercises; more variety of exercises; lots of context &amp;amp; background for every exercise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a full-day workshop - to be honest, I don&#39;t think a half-day workshop on React would be enough to really get someone started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Oodles and oodles of thanks to this group, who&amp;#39;ve hung out with me all day long to talk about &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/reactjs?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@reactjs&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/devup2018?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#devup2018&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/WKhkmUnhEm&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/WKhkmUnhEm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Steven Hicks (@pepopowitz) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pepopowitz/status/1049406551994306560?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;October 8, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;And A Trail Half Marathon!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Staying fit is as important to me as sharing with the tech community. I&#39;ve raced about 3 triathlons a summer with my partner the last few years, and I&#39;ve considered myself a mountain biker for the last 20 years. In 2018 I learned that I really really loved trail running. So much so that I&#39;ve shifted my identity from &amp;quot;mountain biker&amp;quot; to &amp;quot;trail runner&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have long said that I never wanted to run more than a 10k, but something about a half marathon on trail got me excited. I raced the North Face Endurance Challenge 10k in September of 2017, and loved it - this was enough to convince me I could do a half marathon in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I did it! And I loved it. And it went great. Except the part where I forgot my water bottle at home. This was a bigger deal than you&#39;d think - there was a 5 mile stretch in between water stations, and I drink a lot while I run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Step 1: Find something you love to do.&lt;br&gt;Step 2: Find a good support system. &lt;br&gt;Step 3: Do more of the thing you love to do, with help from your support system.&lt;br&gt;Step 4: Happiness.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;/fin &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/kEp7QXl2y9&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/kEp7QXl2y9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Steven Hicks (@pepopowitz) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pepopowitz/status/1041502063824457728?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;September 17, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;And A Road Half Marathon!&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Finished my second half marathon 45 seconds ahead of my A-goal. The weather was a perfect 45°F. The beer tent was cozy. My wife missed her A-goal by a couple minutes, but this was her first half marathon, she did great, and I&amp;#39;m super proud of her. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/3KVTb5tXYr&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/3KVTb5tXYr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Steven Hicks (@pepopowitz) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pepopowitz/status/1058814295474143232?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;November 3, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;And A New Job! (Again)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started a new job in December, 2017. I didn&#39;t really enjoy it, for a variety of reasons. I knew pretty quickly that it was a temporary stop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In June 2018, I met &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jonallured&quot;&gt;Jon Allured&lt;/a&gt; at Open Source North. We completely hit it off, and hung out a bunch that day. Within a couple weeks, he introduced me to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.artsy.net&quot;&gt;Artsy&lt;/a&gt;, and I started a long interview process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October, 2018, I started as an engineer at Artsy. I&#39;m working out of my basement, as the main office is in New York City. I love everything about it. I&#39;m learning a ton. I&#39;m becoming a Rails developer, which is a strange thing for me to say. One thing I know for sure - &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.blog/2018-12-07-octoverse-emoji-on-github/&quot;&gt;ruby developers use ❤️ emojis A LOT&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Cream City Code&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October, we held the first ever Cream City Code - a re-branded MKE DOT NET. I&#39;ve helped organize this conference the last few years, and the day of the event is an absolute blast for me. Unfortunately, I missed most of it this year, due to a conflict. CCC was bigger than ever this year, and the team continues to get better at putting on this event. I am really proud of the lineup we put together for speakers this year - yet bummed that I barely got to see any of them 😢.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Burnout&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;October was an absolute mess for me. I wrote a full-day workshop for dev Up Conference, spoke twice &amp;amp; led that workshop at dev Up, helped put on Cream City Code, started my new job and spent the first week in NYC, and spoke at MKE JS. Most of that happened in the first couple weeks of October. Things were rough at home, as I was spending a lot of time with people that weren&#39;t my family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had another event scheduled for October - LibertyJS. I had to cancel it. I felt really awful, but I did a really bad job of planning my month. In the end, I decided I would rather have the organizers of LibertyJS hate me than have my partner and kids hate me. I backed out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I burned myself out. By the end of October, I didn&#39;t want to spend a minute of my free-time away from my family. I skipped Milwaukee Code Camp - an event that means a lot to me, as a local free event for the community. I just didn&#39;t have it in me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m mostly over the burnout now. I did it to myself, though, and I need to be more mindful of my schedule in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2019&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s my 2018. What&#39;s ahead for 2019?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Less Speaking&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at open CFPs, I have a lot of conflicts for events that I&#39;d like to submit to. I&#39;m also doing a better job of communicating with my partner about the events that are on my radar. There just aren&#39;t nearly as many events I&#39;ll be submitting to this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m okay with this. The nice thing about less speaking is that I&#39;ll have more time for writing. I think I&#39;ll be able to meet my goal pace of one article per month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hardest part is that I&#39;m not able to submit to two of my absolute favorite conferences: Open Source North and Self.conference. Hopefully things align better in 2020. (Holy crap. Next year is 2020.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;More Workshops!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, I now have a really solid React workshop that I&#39;m planning on giving more often. I&#39;m submitting it to conferences, but I also plan on running it in Milwaukee a couple times, for the community here. I&#39;ll charge enough to get a space paid for and some food, and maybe enough money to buy myself a beer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Year of Trail Running&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ❤️ trail running. I love it. I&#39;ve got several races on my calendar already for this year - including 2 half marathons, and a 9 mile race. I dream of a future where I am a crazy ultra-marathon runner. I don&#39;t have time for that yet, but this year I want to get my calves pretty dirty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Combining trail races with triathlons and road races, I have 11 races that I&#39;m looking at this year. I might have a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Finding Balance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than anything, I just want to find balance. I don&#39;t want to burn myself out again. I want to feel like I&#39;m giving back to the Milwaukee &amp;amp; midwest dev community, and still have energy left for my family and running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2019 is the year of balance for me. And I wish you the same.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>5 Tips For Writing A Conference Submission</title>
		<link href="/blog/2018/08/tips-for-writing-conference-submissions/"/>
		<updated>2018-08-13T07:00:00-05:00</updated>
		<id>/blog/2018/08/tips-for-writing-conference-submissions/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Writing a winning conference talk submission seems like a dark art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past couple months, I&#39;ve read every word of nearly 250 conference talk submissions. Multiple times. I&#39;m on the speaker committee for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.creamcitycode.com/&quot;&gt;Cream City Code&lt;/a&gt; (nee MKE DOT NET), and we recently finalized our selections for our October 2018 event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I &lt;strong&gt;cannot&lt;/strong&gt; refute the idea that small animal sacrifice or eye of newt will get you into your next tech conference. I &lt;strong&gt;can&lt;/strong&gt; share some tips for writing a submission that I&#39;d love to read, though!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; I&#39;ll pick on myself a little in this article, so as not to pick on anyone else. All examples are based on my own talks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tip 1: Clear titles are better than witty titles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people recommend that you craft a witty title in your submission, to stand out from the others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A better way to stand out is to have a title that tells me (and the attendees) exactly what the talk is about. If you can craft a witty or punny title and still give me full clarity on the talk subject, that&#39;s great. But I will not dock you for a simple, straightforward title like &amp;quot;Building A Blog With Static Website Generation.&amp;quot; It tells me what I&#39;m going to learn about!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, a title like &amp;quot;Back-ends? Where we&#39;re going, we don&#39;t need...back-ends...&amp;quot; is a super awesome reference to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=flge_rw6RG0&quot;&gt;a great movie&lt;/a&gt;, but it doesn&#39;t tell the reviewers what the talk is about. Worse, it doesn&#39;t tell &lt;strong&gt;the attendees&lt;/strong&gt; what the talk is about. So when they check the schedule right before the next session, deciding where to go next, they will skip over your talk and find a title they understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experience, talks don&#39;t get accepted/rejected &lt;strong&gt;by conference organizers&lt;/strong&gt; based on title alone. They do get chosen/skipped &lt;strong&gt;by attendees&lt;/strong&gt; based on title alone, though. Help them find the right session by using a clear title.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tip 2: Don&#39;t stress out about the &amp;quot;elevator pitch&amp;quot;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We use &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.papercall.io/&quot;&gt;Papercall&lt;/a&gt; to manage our CFP. Papercall provides two fields for people to describe their talk: Abstract and Description.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Description is not character-limited. Abstract is limited, though, to 300 characters. Characters - not words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is &lt;strong&gt;really hard&lt;/strong&gt; to write something worthwhile in 300 characters. There are a few strategies I&#39;ve seen (or used) to maximize the 300 characters:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cut sentences/phrases out of the Description field to get it down to 300&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write a single sentence that is a lengthy version of the title&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apply SEO skills, and pack keywords&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these result in something that is pretty much meaningless to me. I&#39;ve stopped reading the Abstract field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m sure I&#39;m an outlier on this, and you should definitely still fill this in for submissions to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.creamcitycode.com/&quot;&gt;Cream City Code&lt;/a&gt; and other events. But your efforts are better spent on the Description than the 300-character Abstract.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tip 3: Tell me why I should attend, and what I&#39;ll walk away with&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes we get submissions where the Description field is about the same length as the 300-character Abstract field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I almost always down-vote these submissions, for lack of information. The Description field is not character-limited. It ends up on the website, and in the printed program. This is what attendees read to decide where to go - give them a good idea of what they&#39;re going to learn about!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several components I love to see in a Description:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a common pain-point, or an explanation why the talk is important&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a brief description of the main topic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a few things I&#39;ll take away from the talk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These components lead again to clarity: not only for me, but for the people looking for a session to attend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important thing your Description does is get the right audience in the room. You don&#39;t want &lt;strong&gt;everyone&lt;/strong&gt; to attend your talk, you want the people who will most benefit from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you describe a problem, the solution, and some takeaways, you&#39;ll get the right attendees in your session. You&#39;ll also help the organizers feel confident about the lineup they&#39;re putting together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s also important to note that you can write a Description that far exceeds 300 characters, but still doesn&#39;t give me enough information. Don&#39;t add fluff to make your Description longer. Add words that are meaningful, and that add value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tip 4: A few small errors are fine...but not too many&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the second grade, I took second place in the Oconomowoc School District spelling bee. I lost on the word &amp;quot;embarrassed.&amp;quot; The jokes wrote themselves: &amp;quot;It&#39;s okay, Steve! Don&#39;t be...(wait for it)...&lt;strong&gt;EMBARRASSED&lt;/strong&gt;!!!&amp;quot; To this day, I am convinced I spelled it correctly, and the judges did not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is to say, I am an above average speller. I am also married to an English teacher - and I think there is a super-secret English teacher test for potential partners, to weed out the grammatically deficient. So I think I&#39;m above average at grammar, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple small errors will get noticed by me, but I&#39;ll look past them. We all make mistakes - I once submitted a cover letter with the wrong company name! I&#39;m willing to overlook a couple small issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I won&#39;t overlook a submission with lots of spelling or grammar errors. It makes me think you haven&#39;t thought much beyond the abstract. If you don&#39;t care about the quality of your submission, I&#39;m not sure you&#39;ll care about the quality of your talk. Most of all, I&#39;m worried you might not do a great job of communicating to the audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use tools to check your spelling and grammar. Use &lt;a href=&quot;http://hemingwayapp.com/&quot;&gt;Hemingway&lt;/a&gt; or a similar tool to reduce the reading level of your submission. If you struggle with grammar and spelling, have someone review your submission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tip 5: Please don&#39;t make people feel bad&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes things are worded in a way that I feel like I&#39;m an idiot, or not smart enough to attend your session. If I&#39;m a WordPress developer, the sentence &amp;quot;If you&#39;re still using WordPress, you&#39;re doing it wrong.&amp;quot; makes me feel bad about myself. I&#39;ll admit that I&#39;m pretty sensitive - but if your abstract makes me feel bad about myself, I&#39;m not going to attend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You probably intend to be funny. You and your officemates maybe say things like &amp;quot;you&#39;re doing it wrong&amp;quot; as a joke, and you laugh with each other. I get that. But I still don&#39;t like it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Submissions with exclusive/gate-keeper language like this are a red flag to me. They worry me that someone will attend your session who doesn&#39;t get your jokes. That you won&#39;t have a good sense of your audience, and you&#39;ll push the jokes too far. And that we&#39;ll have to have a conversation that none of us are happy about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Keep submitting your talk!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these recommendations are based on my preferences. Different conferences are organized by different people with different preferences. Even within &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.creamcitycode.com/&quot;&gt;Cream City Code&lt;/a&gt;, there are differences in the preferences of all 6 reviewers. (This is intentional, and a benefit. We want different preferences, to give the lineup a good balance.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one of the main reasons conference talk submission seems like a dark art. What gets you into one conference won&#39;t get you into another. Different reviewers are looking for different things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The large majority of submissions to conferences are well-written. Conferences just don&#39;t have room for them all. At &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.creamcitycode.com/&quot;&gt;Cream City Code&lt;/a&gt;, we start with our highest-rated sessions, then fit other highly-rated sessions around them to give broad topic coverage. There are a lot of really good submissions that we just can&#39;t pick, because we only have 30 slots!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you submit to a conference and don&#39;t get in, there&#39;s a good chance you did nothing wrong. Please don&#39;t take it personally. Keep submitting!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s all about finding a group of reviewers with which your talk resonates.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>10 Tips For Writing Conference Talks</title>
		<link href="/blog/2018/04/tips-for-writing-talks/"/>
		<updated>2018-04-22T07:00:00-05:00</updated>
		<id>/blog/2018/04/tips-for-writing-talks/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;div&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;half-scale&quot; src=&quot;../anxiety-over-time.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My anxiety while preparing for a talk looks like a saw.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Speaking is fun, you should try it.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the last couple years, my priorities in life have been three things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My family&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being active&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speaking at tech meetups &amp;amp; conferences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking is pretty new for me. My first talk in public was in February, 2016. In the last couple years, I&#39;ve given over 20 talks at local meetups and code camps, and conferences throughout the Midwest. It&#39;s been a ton of fun, and I highly recommend trying it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve learned &lt;strong&gt;a ton&lt;/strong&gt; about speaking in the last couple years. Here are 10 things I&#39;ve learned about preparing a conference or meetup talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tip 1: Keep your thoughts organized.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It takes me months to write a talk. Often I have multiple ideas formulating at the same time. If I tried to keep all of the different ideas in my brain, I would lose about 95% of them. I need tools to keep track of it all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To stay organized, I use two main tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Trello&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I keep a Trello board to keep track of all my speaking ideas, talks, submissions, and upcoming engagements. This is high-level stuff, just so I know what I need to be working on every night. I have lists for conferences I want to submit to, open CFPs, abstracts I need to write, talks I&#39;m writing, and talks that are ready to submit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Git Repository&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a Git repository that contains all my talks. This is more detailed than what&#39;s in my Trello board. Abstracts, outlines, slides - it&#39;s all in the repo. I wrestle back and forth about whether this should be private or public. It is currently private.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tip 2: Get outside. Creativity comes from many places.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of my ideas don&#39;t come while I&#39;m working. I do a lot of thinking and workshopping ideas in my head in a few key places - in the shower, in bed when I fall asleep/wake up, listening to podcasts in my car, and above all during workouts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I generally prefer working out by myself, because it&#39;s my best thinking time. I feel bad when people ask me if I am looking for a workout buddy, because unless it&#39;s my wife, the answer is almost entirely no. I really like being social with people, but exercise is such a personal thing to me. It&#39;s actually the only time I can think of that I&#39;ll say &amp;quot;no&amp;quot; to company. It&#39;s just such a valuable time for my mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My ideas usually take months before I even turn them into a conference submission. They simmer in my brain. I work through outlines and brainstorms, making sure that I have enough of a cohesive message to deliver it to an audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tip 3: Keep a notebook on you at all times.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ideas come at all times. I&#39;ve lost enough ideas in the past that I want to be able to write them down as soon as I get them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I take notes as I think of things. My daughters make me these awesome pocket-sized notebooks out of printer paper, and I keep them in a slim wallet case in my pocket, along with a pen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have become my father. :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the things I write down are points I want to make, sometimes they are jokes, sometimes they are drawings I want to include. Sometimes they are just the way I want to deliver a specific point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tip 4: Don&#39;t apply force to an idea. Let it present itself.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I feel like an idea has legs, but I just can&#39;t find the overall message. I&#39;ve found that forcing it to become something is less effective than waiting for it to present itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I hit a brick wall with an idea, I still add it to my Trello board. If it&#39;s a good idea, it will eventually work its way back to the front of my thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favorite talk - &lt;a href=&quot;https://steven-j-hicks-speaking.netlify.com/do-scary-things&quot;&gt;Maximize Professional Growth By Doing Scary Things&lt;/a&gt; - took 9 months to graduate from an idea to an outline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I feel like I have enough notes &amp;amp; ideas to deliver it to an audience, it becomes an outline. I give it a folder in my Git repo. I build an outline out of all the notes I&#39;ve written down. They are often scatterbrained and messy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I let it simmer some more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tip 5: Start with content and a message. Save the slides for last.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ll work for a month or so at building an outline. At this stage, I&#39;m mostly worried about two things - all of the content I think is worth delivering, and a single message I want my audience to walk away with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I prefer a simple nested outline, in a text editor. It&#39;s quick and easy for me to move things around. I&#39;ve heard others say they use mind-mapping software at this stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t start writing abstracts or slides until I&#39;ve got a rough outline and a message established.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tip 6: Don&#39;t write an abstract if you aren&#39;t certain you can write the talk.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first started trying to get into speaking, I didn&#39;t have much restraint on the abstracts I submitted. I wrote and submitted as many as I could think of, with little thought to how I would fill 45 minutes. This got me in trouble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once, I found that I had to write a talk that I wasn&#39;t really interested in. This was very hard to do, and I just kept procrastinating. I eventually reached out to the &amp;quot;organizers&amp;quot; (who happened to be my coworkers) and asked if I could change topics. Thankfully, I could.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also found that I had too many talks to write this way. Different conferences picked up different ideas, and I had to write them all. This is probably normal when you&#39;re starting out, but I think my tendency to abstract without a solid idea of the content exacerbated the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I don&#39;t feel like I can write a solid abstract without a good outline. The outline isn&#39;t finalized at this stage - but it gives me a good idea of what&#39;s in the talk, so that I can summarize it with confidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing my abstract takes me many tries. I&#39;ll throw a few attempts in a markdown file in my repo, and none of them are usually what I end up with. I pick and choose from all the attempts, and assemble them into something I feel good about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tip 7: Get feedback from people. Sort the feedback before you address it.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Armed with a rough draft of an abstract, I&#39;ll reach out to a few friends, and ask them for feedback. I generally ask a few key people who I know will give me the kind of feedback I&#39;m looking for. It takes time to determine who you can trust to give you good feedback, but it&#39;s worth the effort to find out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you get helpful, constructive feedback, it helps you improve your ideas &amp;amp; abstracts tremendously. But even with feedback from people you trust, not all feedback is worth addressing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, you get feedback that is more about the person giving the feedback, and less about your abstract. It could be a suggestion that you rewrite your talk to be about something they&#39;re more interested in. It might be that their past experiences influence their opinions of what you&#39;ve written. Feedback from friends almost always comes from good intentions - but I&#39;ve found it important to sort the feedback I get. I will generally only address feedback with the following characteristics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is definitely about my idea or abstract.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is specific. We have an idea on how I can improve it, or we can at least identify what the problem is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is more than just an opinion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that I don&#39;t like feedback - I love it. I&#39;ll continue to ask for feedback, and you should too. It&#39;s just important to recognize when it is actually something you can/should address.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tip 8: Remember that your talk is for the audience.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I&#39;m turning my outline into a full-length talk, I often have to remind myself that the talk isn&#39;t for me - it&#39;s for the people listening. Even if it&#39;s a story I&#39;m telling about my experiences, people aren&#39;t listening to &lt;strong&gt;me&lt;/strong&gt; - they are listening to my message. They aren&#39;t interested in how &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; got through a problem, they are interested in how my experiences could help &lt;strong&gt;them&lt;/strong&gt; get through their problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I focus on optimizing the flow of the information. I want my listeners to digest the topic with as little effort as possible. I once resorted to a card-sorting exercise, because I just couldn&#39;t work out the flow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Sometimes, putting together a talk looks more like this than &amp;quot;making slides.&amp;quot; Trying to find a way to fit pieces together to make it flow. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/LGbh3dkn63&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/LGbh3dkn63&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Steven Hicks (@pepopowitz) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pepopowitz/status/909875532120170498?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;September 18, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want my talks to be (1) clear, (2) inspiring, and (3) entertaining. Making this happen is usually harder than identifying the content &amp;amp; message. I spend a lot of time editing my talk to meet these goals. The attendees paid to be at the conference, though, and I didn&#39;t - so any effort I can put in to give them more value is worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tip 9: The perfect image is hard to find. Make your own!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When my outline approaches &amp;quot;good enough,&amp;quot; I finally start to build my slides. I use a tool called &lt;a href=&quot;http://remarkjs.com/&quot;&gt;RemarkJS&lt;/a&gt; for my slides. It&#39;s an HTML/CSS/JS-based presentation tool, and it allows me to write all my slides in Markdown. Since I already have an outline in a text file, it&#39;s pretty easy to turn that into Markdown slides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I&#39;m doing this, I start thinking about imagery. Images add a lot to your slides, but they have to be the right images. Showing an unrelated image can distract listeners - they spend time trying to decipher how the image relates, instead of listening to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve spent a lot of time looking for the right images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early on, I would do an image search on Google. This takes more time than you think - especially if you&#39;re looking for something specific.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve used sites like &lt;a href=&quot;//unsplash.com&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;//pexels.com&quot;&gt;Pexels&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;//flickr.com&quot;&gt;Flickr&lt;/a&gt;, and these all have great images. They still take a lot of time when you&#39;re looking for something specific, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;//twitter.com/reverentgeek&quot;&gt;David Neal&lt;/a&gt;, I started drawing my own images on an iPad. Initially, they were bad. Even today, many of them are not great. But they add two major benefits to my talks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They add a personal touch to the slides. People overwhelmingly appreciate this, and comment on it often.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I spend significantly less time drawing all my images than I spent searching for them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I get to a point in my slide preparation where all I want to do is draw images. It&#39;s therapeutic, and it breaks up the monotony of building out slides and practicing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;half-scale&quot; src=&quot;../pizza.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My oven sets off a smoke alarm every time I cook a pizza.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;Seriously, though. Try to find a good image of an oven that sets off a smoke alarm every time you cook a pizza in it.&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tip 10: Find The Way That Works For You&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re interested in presenting at tech meetups and conferences, or getting better, you should &lt;a href=&quot;https://channel9.msdn.com/Shows/On-NET/Public-speaking-with-Scott-Hanselman-Kendra-Havens-Maria-Naggaga-Nakanwagi-Kasey-Uhlenhuth-and-Donov&quot;&gt;watch this video from MSDN&lt;/a&gt;. There are a ton of good tips in it, but my favorite that comes out of it is from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/shanselman&quot;&gt;Scott Hanselman&lt;/a&gt; -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find the way that works for you, and do it unapologetically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This applies to so much more than just speaking, but it is definitely applicable here. In the past couple years, I&#39;ve watched more videos and read more tweets and articles about speaking than 99% of the world. The one thing I can say for certain is that the process is different for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I effectively script every talk that I do. I rely on my notes as I speak. I don&#39;t read them word for word, but I have thought through almost every word I&#39;m going to say ahead of time. I do this because I&#39;m afraid that if I ramble, I&#39;m going to say things I regret. Scripting your talk goes against almost every speaker&#39;s advice. But it works for me, because it makes me feel more comfortable when I&#39;m up there, and I can deliver those lines without sounding like a robot. (I think.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also don&#39;t practice very much. This also goes against most speakers&#39; advice. Many even say &amp;quot;you should practice so much you&#39;re bored with your talk.&amp;quot; But I spend so much time with the ideas bouncing around in my brain, and editing my outline, and editing my outline some more, that I don&#39;t feel like I need a ton of practice. By the time I&#39;ve actually built my slide deck, I know most of the content pretty well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And really, that&#39;s all that matters when you&#39;re writing a talk - do what works for you. If you don&#39;t know what works for you, try some things that you think might. You&#39;ll find out pretty quickly if they don&#39;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different strokes for different folks, as they say.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>On Overcoming Rejection</title>
		<link href="/blog/2018/01/on-overcoming-rejection/"/>
		<updated>2018-03-01T06:00:00-06:00</updated>
		<id>/blog/2018/01/on-overcoming-rejection/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;2017 was huge for me. After discovering that I wanted to get into speaking at conferences, in 2017 I made those dreams a reality. I attacked the conference submission season with reckless abandon. I was going to submit anywhere, and let &lt;strong&gt;them&lt;/strong&gt; tell me &amp;quot;no&amp;quot; instead of telling &lt;strong&gt;myself&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;quot;no.&amp;quot; There was some rejection here and there, but also a lot of success. At one point, I had received so many acceptances that I started retracting submissions. There are only so many weekends in a Wisconsin summer, and I didn&#39;t want to fill them all with conferences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of 2017, I&#39;d spoken at a handful of events, and I was feeling really good about what 2018 would bring. Things got off to a good start. In the fall of 2017, I got accepted to two 2018 events - &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.codemash.org/&quot;&gt;CodeMash&lt;/a&gt; in Ohio and &lt;a href=&quot;http://webcon.illinois.edu/&quot;&gt;WebCon&lt;/a&gt; in Illinois.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I&#39;d done a bad job of reading my calendar. When I shared the news with my wife, she reminded me that we had planned on taking the kids somewhere for spring break the week of WebCon. I avoided sending the email to WebCon for a week or two - but I had to decline the invite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Karma&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second I sent the email, I said out loud &amp;quot;I&#39;ve got some bad karma coming my way.&amp;quot; One of the things I hate most in life is saying you&#39;ll do something, then backing out. Whether it&#39;s going to a concert, meeting for lunch, speaking at a conference, whatever - I am a reliable person, and doing things that chip away at my reliability make me mad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, I received a notice from &lt;a href=&quot;https://ndcoslo.com/&quot;&gt;NDC Oslo 2018&lt;/a&gt; that my sessions were not accepted. Nevermind the fact that NDC is a notoriously difficult conference to get into, and that I probably don&#39;t have the experience yet to get into an international conference. All I could think was &amp;quot;this is my 11th straight conference rejection since I sent that email to WebCon! It&#39;s obviously karma! @#$#@$!#$@#!!!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After venting to some friends about how frustrated I am, I am done with this nonsense. This whole WebCon/karma/0-11 thing is just a story I keep telling myself. It&#39;s got a nice narrative quality to it. It would make good TV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it&#39;s stupid. It&#39;s just a set of events that happened. It doesn&#39;t define me. I let it define me in my self-talk, too much. But I know that it doesn&#39;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In talking to people recently about how frustrated I am with my &amp;quot;curse,&amp;quot; one suggestion consistently arose. &amp;quot;Stop it. Channel this into something productive.&amp;quot; So with that, here are some things we all need to remember to do when we are feeling rejected. Yes, &amp;quot;we.&amp;quot; This is as much for me as it is for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Talk To Someone&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is probably the simplest and most obvious thing we can do. But I&#39;m saying it anyway - because sometimes I forget to do it, so maybe you do too. I&#39;ve let this karma storyline fester in my mind for a long time. Saying it out loud to people helps me remember that &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;I&#39;M JOKING&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and this is not a thing to actually believe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully you have someone who is better at &lt;strong&gt;listening&lt;/strong&gt; than I am (developers just want to fix things!). Saying things to someone else feels so much better than saying them to yourself. This is probably because we treat ourselves like total crap with our self-talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Change Your Self-Talk&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about the things you say to yourself when things aren&#39;t going your way. It&#39;s not good, right? Today I said to myself &amp;quot;Why the f*** am I doing this anymore?&amp;quot; I actually said that to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/davidpine7&quot;&gt;David Pine&lt;/a&gt;, too. He correctly told me to stop being a dummy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&#39;d never say those awful words about a friend who was struggling. &amp;quot;Why the f*** are you still doing that? You&#39;re terrible at it.&amp;quot; Even writing it as a hypothetical situation feels ridiculous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Treat yourself like you&#39;d treat your friends. Build yourself up. Don&#39;t tear yourself down. Again, maybe this is obvious to you. It&#39;s obvious to me too, but it doesn&#39;t mean that I don&#39;t forget to do it sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Find A Mantra&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mantras are a big help for me getting through challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For sports-y things, the one I always use is &amp;quot;Come on.&amp;quot; This is a thing that rock-climbers say a lot to each other, especially when bouldering, as they are about to make a tough move. I&#39;m actually not totally sure if it&#39;s a thing ALL rock climbers say, or if it&#39;s just a thing that they say at the gym I climb at. It&#39;s a phrase that I say to myself when I need a confidence boost. It gives me instant strength and power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&#39;t really have a mantra for rejection, until today. I found this one &lt;a href=&quot;http://alwayswellwithin.com/2015/09/27/mantras-to-boost-confidence/&quot;&gt;on the internet&lt;/a&gt;, and I like it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My &amp;quot;failures&amp;quot; are stepping stones to success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it is something I&#39;m going to keep around, for moments like today. Maybe repeating a mantra can help you, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Meditate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m trying to get more regular at meditation. One of the things that really helped me get into speaking was weekly guided meditation from my yoga instructor. I&#39;ve struggled to find time to do it since then, but I think I just recently found a time that I can get 5 minutes in every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meditation has been really helpful for me. If you haven&#39;t tried it, or it&#39;s been a while, I recommend it. I use the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.whil.com/&quot;&gt;whil&lt;/a&gt; app because it is free through work, but I wouldn&#39;t hesitate to try another one. If you&#39;re pretty good with focus, you probably don&#39;t even need an app. Sometimes I just need it to keep me from chasing shiny things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I finished venting about my NDC rejection, the first thing I did was a &amp;quot;confidence&amp;quot; meditation. It helped a ton. It is a guaranteed and immediate way to change your self-talk. Try it some time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Promote The Things That Are Working&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some things that have gone my way during the time that I&#39;ve been declined by 11 conferences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I got a new job, and I really like it!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I spoke at CodeMash! That&#39;s also a pretty hard conference to get into!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While I was there, I got to hang out with the guy who inspired me to start speaking at conferences! We talked about our families!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also while I was there, I put together a lightning talk in one day, and it was the most fun talk I&#39;ve ever given!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just today, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/raelyard&quot;&gt;Dave Rael&lt;/a&gt; released a new &lt;a href=&quot;http://developeronfire.com/podcast/episode-317-steven-hicks-scary-things&quot;&gt;Developer On Fire&lt;/a&gt; podcast episode, featuring me! This is awesome. The guests he has on are some of my heroes. To even be &lt;strong&gt;CONSIDERED&lt;/strong&gt; to be on his podcast is an honor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I scheduled a time to talk to Clark Sell on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLbvKfz3RGx_zTquL6x028DYufot2v5Ddr&quot;&gt;AskTHAT&lt;/a&gt; series! This is exactly the kind of stuff I want to do to propel myself into speaking greatness!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other things I&#39;m not remembering or can&#39;t really talk about!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of worrying about how long the streak is going to go before I get accepted, I&#39;m going to tell people about that stuff. Maybe this approach of promoting the positive can help us focus on the things that make us feel good about ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Create Something&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a lot of negative energy when I got the NDC email. That kind of energy doesn&#39;t really help anyone. Again, we all know this....this is just a friendly reminder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Channeling that energy into this post has been really helpful. It&#39;s removed the thoughts of &amp;quot;Why am I still even trying???&amp;quot; from my head, and replaced them with ideas. Ideas that will become blog posts, and talks, and abstracts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, channeling the energy means &amp;quot;producing something helpful.&amp;quot; For you, channeling it might mean &amp;quot;expressing your feelings&amp;quot;. The medium might be art, it might be writing, it might even be code. Whatever it is, creative energy is so much more valuable than destructive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know you know these things. I know them too. Let&#39;s keep reminding each other, okay?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Keep Laying Seeds&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I woke up today, I was frustrated about rejection #10, which I&#39;d received last night. Lying in bed, I reminded myself something I&#39;ve been thinking a lot lately -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just keep laying seeds. Eventually some of them will grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This afternoon, I overheard a coworker say almost the exact same thing about buying stocks. I consider this to be official confirmation that this is a good approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m going to keep throwing submissions at conference CFPs. I hope you lay more seeds, too. If we keep it up, eventually one is going to grow like Jack&#39;s beanstalk.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>2017 In Review</title>
		<link href="/blog/2018/01/2017-in-review/"/>
		<updated>2018-01-31T06:00:00-06:00</updated>
		<id>/blog/2018/01/2017-in-review/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;2017&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People say scary things about turning 40. Your body hurts more. You wonder if you&#39;re doing the right thing with your life. You just feel sleepy all the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2017 was my 40th year on this planet. While I won&#39;t totally argue with some of the things people say about being 40, I will also say this - I hope every year can be as good as my 40th year was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Speaking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my goals in 2017 was to get out and speak a ton. I had a goal of speaking 12 times - averaging once per month. I nailed that exactly! In 2017, I gave....&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6 talks at conferences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 talks at code camps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 talks at meetups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talk I gave most was &lt;a href=&quot;https://steven-j-hicks-speaking.netlify.com/getting-started-with-react&quot;&gt;Getting Started With React&lt;/a&gt;. This was a surprise for me - I hadn&#39;t even considered doing an &amp;quot;intro&amp;quot; style talk at the beginning of the year. I figured no one would want to hear &amp;quot;another intro.&amp;quot; I was wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Self.conference&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;It&amp;#39;s going to take me a couple days to digest all the amazing ideas for being a better person and dev &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/selfconference?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@selfconference&lt;/a&gt;. 10/10 will do again.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Steven Hicks (@pepopowitz) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pepopowitz/status/866071098718392329?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 20, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In May, I got to speak at Self.conference, in Detroit. As you can see, I was not prepared for this experience. I&#39;ve been to conferences before, but I&#39;ve never been to one that affected me so much emotionally. There were so many amazing talks that were focused on making you a better person, not just a better developer. I would love to go back here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/crebma&quot;&gt;@crebma&lt;/a&gt; keeps Self.conference going for many more years, so people can experience what I did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Open Source North&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;.&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/OpenSourceNorth?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@OpenSourceNorth&lt;/a&gt; has a Japanese garden right outside the doors and it. is. glorious. Best conference amenity ever. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/osn2017?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#osn2017&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/MzzIiMuZiY&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/MzzIiMuZiY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Steven Hicks (@pepopowitz) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pepopowitz/status/872875607843119104?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;June 8, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wasn&#39;t sure what to expect when I made the trip up to the Twin Cities in June, for Open Source North. I came away really impressed with the conference, and especially the organizers. I got some really great tips from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jeffurban&quot;&gt;Jeff Urban&lt;/a&gt; about how we could improve the organization of &lt;a href=&quot;http://mkedotnet.com&quot;&gt;MKE DOT NET&lt;/a&gt;. I would go back to this conference in a heartbeat, if they&#39;d have me. I think I did pretty well!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;The most amazing talk of the day nod goes to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pepopowitz?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@pepopowitz&lt;/a&gt; -- engaging presentation, exciting content. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/staticweb?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#staticweb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Rachel Walwood (@walwoodr) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/walwoodr/status/872916663108329472?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;June 8, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;That Conference&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That Conference is where I was originally bitten by the speaking bug - in 2015, when I saw &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/housecor&quot;&gt;Cory House&lt;/a&gt; give two talks, and was blown away by his command of the room. Getting to speak here in 2017 was amazing. It made me feel like I&#39;d really done what I set out to do - become a conference speaker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shortly before my talk, I ran into &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/davidgiard&quot;&gt;David Giard&lt;/a&gt;, another of my speaker heroes, in the speaker lounge. My voice crackled as I told him how much he inspired me, and how much it meant for me to be speaking at the same event as him. He was extremely gracious, as always - and then asked when and where my talk was, so he could attend. This was not exactly what I was expecting, and suddenly I felt a bit of pressure to impress him. Cut to fifteen minutes into my talk, with him applauding me and practically rolling out of his chair with laughter, and I felt like I did pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My wife and kids attended my talk, too! This was really fun, and I hope they can be in the audience for more of my talks. I felt like I made them proud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;MidwestJS&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Borked my phone this morning in the rain. Resorting to 19th century tactics to commemorate a fun speaker dinner &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/midwest_js?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@midwest_js&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/midwestjs?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#midwestjs&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/K3ywDFxQvm&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/K3ywDFxQvm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Steven Hicks (@pepopowitz) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pepopowitz/status/898008069271166976?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;August 17, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My second trip to the Twin Cities for a conference. I went for a run one morning, and a surprise &lt;em&gt;massive&lt;/em&gt; downpour soaked my phone - and turned it into a hunk o&#39; junk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was another case of the organizers just being fantastic. One thing I think is really important for speakers is to be very gracious and thankful with the organizers. When they do as great a job as MidwestJS did, it makes it easy to be gracious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Dev Up&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October, we took the kids out of school for a couple days to make a family trip to Dev Up, in St. Louis. We spent a weekend being tourists, and had a ton of fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Got to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/devupconf?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@devupconf&lt;/a&gt; a little early and spent some family time being tourists. 630 feet of fun. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/TMEXwdx2bh&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/TMEXwdx2bh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Steven Hicks (@pepopowitz) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pepopowitz/status/919330189657673728?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;October 14, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a new talk to deliver here - &lt;a href=&quot;https://steven-j-hicks-speaking.netlify.com/do-scary-things/&quot;&gt;Maximize Professional Growth By Doing Scary Things&lt;/a&gt;. This is a talk I&#39;d had floating around in my head for at least a year. I wanted to convince people to do something scary, in hopes that it would change their life - the way that getting into speaking has changed mine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was emotionally drained during the conference, because I was just so nervous about this talk. It is the most vulnerable thing I&#39;ve done. It took me a lot of energy to build myself up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It went awesome, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;One of my favorite &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/devup2017?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#devup2017&lt;/a&gt; talks was from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pepopowitz?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@pepopowitz&lt;/a&gt; talking about fear. Feeling inspired. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/9VFZACcWSD&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/9VFZACcWSD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Scott Addie (@Scott_Addie) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Scott_Addie/status/920336252280475649?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;October 17, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was great to have &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/davidpine7&quot;&gt;David Pine&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Scott_Addie&quot;&gt;Scott Addie&lt;/a&gt; - two friends from home - in the front row for this talk. I needed the encouragement, and they delivered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;MKE DOT NET&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was year number 3 for MKE DOT NET. I&#39;ve helped out with all three - but never as much as this year. I was significantly involved from start to finish of the planning this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I love it. The day of MKE DOT NET is like Christmas for me. I love the adrenyline of getting to the event early in the morning, and discovering that a marathon is blocking traffic from getting there. It sucks that this kind of thing happens..but it does, every time. We never know what the problem is going to be - but something is going to go wrong, and we need to figure out how to work around it. Dealing with all of the logistical details of a conference gives me a buzz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;I Got A New Job&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the last few years, Centare has been an incubator for me. I&#39;ve grown so much, thanks largely to the amazing team around me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In late 2017, I found myself looking for new work. I moved on to Northwestern Mutual - a place that I think is poised to make some noise. I&#39;m really excited about my new team and new role. I&#39;m doing full-stack JavaScript. This is a change, after spending almost my whole career in .NET development. It is a welcome change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will continue to help out with MKE DOT NET.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2018 - A Look Ahead&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve got a ton of ideas for 2018. I won&#39;t be able to follow through on all of them, I&#39;m sure. There are just too many.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Not As Much Speaking&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;d really like to keep the momentum with speaking at conferences, but it looks like I won&#39;t be submitting to nearly as many as I&#39;d like this year. It seems as if there are basically four weeks that all conferences are scheduled this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;More Writing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I say this every year. But I re-wrote my blog using &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/11ty/eleventy/&quot;&gt;eleventy&lt;/a&gt; last week, hoping that it provides less friction for writing than Metalsmith did. Metalsmith was a bit flaky, and I would often have to restart the dev server just to get it to reload a content change. So far, eleventy has been great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve already published one story to Medium - &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@pepopowitz/chekhovs-gun-and-better-unit-tests-96fb439e6d0e&quot;&gt;Chekhov&#39;s Gun And Better Unit Tests&lt;/a&gt; - and I&#39;m hoping to write at least 6 Medium-worthy stories this year. Hold me to it, internet!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Self Improvement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m looking to cut back on self-deprecation. I rely on it a lot to make sure people don&#39;t think I&#39;m full of myself - but I&#39;ve found this year that it affects me negatively. I think I believe the self-deprecation a little too much. In 2018, I&#39;m hoping to cut back on this habit significantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve also realized one of my biggest hurdles to feeling comfortable in a social setting with strangers is that I just don&#39;t know how to start conversations. I&#39;m looking into specific ideas to improve this, in the hopes that it makes me feel more confident. Being at a conference where I don&#39;t know anyone can be really draining for me. If I know someone there, or meet someone, it&#39;s a different story - I could talk for hours. I&#39;d like to make it easier for myself to get to that stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Something Scary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not totally sure what, yet. I&#39;ve eliminated live-streaming, as I don&#39;t really understand how it is interesting. Writing is part of this, but I want to do something even more scary. I&#39;m deciding between starting a podcast, and making videos for YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m also going to submit a workshop idea to conferences. I&#39;ve got a basic idea, but I really need to work out more details before I can submit it. I have ideas on how to make a good workshop - but I&#39;m not sure yet how to write an abstract that will get it accepted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;d also like to speak at an international conference this year. I got myself a new passport late in 2017, in hopes that I&#39;d get selected soon. Nothing yet but I&#39;ve got a couple open submissions, and more to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s looking forward to 2018. Let&#39;s get better!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Chekhov&#39;s Gun And Better Unit Tests</title>
		<link href="/blog/2018/01/chekhovs-gun-and-better-unit-tests/"/>
		<updated>2018-01-28T06:00:00-06:00</updated>
		<id>/blog/2018/01/chekhovs-gun-and-better-unit-tests/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../chekhovs-gun.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chekhovs Gun &amp;amp; Unit Testing Illustration&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Chekhov&#39;s Gun&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anton_Chekhov&quot;&gt;Anton Chekhov&lt;/a&gt; was a Russian playwright who died in 1904. He wrote several hundred stories by the time he was 26, many of them highly regarded. Chekhov is often credited with being a major influence on the modern short story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of his most famous contributions is something called Chekhov&#39;s Gun. This is a principle in dramatic writing that suggests that all elements in a story must be relevant in some way. If an element doesn&#39;t have relevance, it should be removed. Irrelevant elements might distract the audience from the intended story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The origin of Chekhov&#39;s Gun comes from several related quotes from his writings. One example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remove everything that has no relevance to the story. If you say in the first chapter that there is a rifle hanging on the wall, in the second or third chapter it absolutely must go off. If it&#39;s not going to be fired, it shouldn&#39;t be hanging there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What does this have to do with unit tests?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from a couple of classes in high school, I’ve never studied writing. I don’t remember the first time I heard of Chekhov’s Gun. It resonated with me though, as an analogy of how I feel about writing unit tests — especially when it comes to test setup. If a line of setup code isn’t important to describe a specific test, then I don’t want it to distract me. I’d like to be able to focus on what makes the test unique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine I have an app where users can submit new beers to a curated list of &amp;quot;the best beers ever.&amp;quot; Here&#39;s a test that I might write for a function that validates that the user submitted the ABV (alcohol by volume) for a beer. We&#39;ll call it &lt;code&gt;Noisy Test&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;describe(&amp;quot;validateBeer&amp;quot;, () =&amp;gt; {
    it(&amp;quot;returns invalid for beers with no abv&amp;quot;, () =&amp;gt; {
        const beer = {
            id: 87983,
            brewery: {
                id: 12332,
                name: &amp;quot;Central Waters&amp;quot;,
                location: &amp;quot;Amherst, WI&amp;quot;,
                overallRating: 5,
            },
            name: &amp;quot;Mudpuppy Porter&amp;quot;,
            beerStyle: &amp;quot;Porter&amp;quot;,
            abv: undefined,
        };

        const result = validateBeer(beer);

        expect(result).toEqual(false);
    });
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Noisy Test&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This test is pretty decent. I like that the name of the test tells me exactly what it is testing. I like that there aren&#39;t a ton of assertions, and it&#39;s pretty clearly testing only one thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I don&#39;t like about it is the distracting setup code. This test verifies that a beer with no ABV is considered invalid. It doesn&#39;t specify &lt;code&gt;abv: undefined&lt;/code&gt; until the 11th line of the test. This means that I have to read through 10 lines of irrelevant setup code before I get to what actually makes this test unique - the submitted beer doesn&#39;t have an ABV. This is a violation of Chekhov&#39;s Gun, in unit test form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I&#39;d rather see is something like this - we&#39;ll call it &lt;code&gt;Better Test&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;describe(&amp;quot;validateBeer&amp;quot;, () =&amp;gt; {
    it(&amp;quot;returns invalid for beers with no abv (less setup)&amp;quot;, () =&amp;gt; {
        const beer = makeMeABeer({
            abv: undefined,
        });

        const result = validateBeer(beer);

        expect(result).toEqual(false);
    });
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Better Test&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, I get a beer from an extracted function named &lt;code&gt;makeMeABeer&lt;/code&gt;. This function would generate a typical beer, with values that are usual and not edge-cases. I pass in only the values that are unique to this test - in this case, &lt;code&gt;abv: undefined&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extracting my setup of a beer, as in the second example, improves my signal to noise ratio for this test. The signal is &amp;quot;what am I trying to test?&amp;quot; The noise, in the first example, is &amp;quot;setup code that doesn&#39;t impact this test.&amp;quot; The more I can increase the signal, the easier it is for a reader of my test to understand my intentions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why do I care about the reader of this test?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A question: who do we write our unit tests for? It&#39;s ourselves, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we&#39;re doing TDD, yes, we get a lot of value out of the tests we&#39;re writing, in the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But aside from TDD, who benefits the most from our tests? It&#39;s not you, when you write the test. You&#39;ve got all the context about the test being written. You most likely understand the code that you are writing. If you&#39;d just finished writing the &lt;code&gt;validateBeer&lt;/code&gt; function, and I asked you what the system was supposed to do with a beer that didn&#39;t have an ABV, you&#39;d likely be able to tell me the answer - without looking at any tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if a teammate makes a change a few months from now and this test suddenly starts failing, that teammate will have no context. They won&#39;t know why this test was written in the first place. They will not know details of how the test was made to pass. They might not even know that ABV is a thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Noisy Test&lt;/code&gt;, a test that is filled with irrelevant setup code, will distract them from discovering why this test exists. It will take them time to determine what makes this test unique compared to the others. They might have to compare it to several other tests to find the difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Better Test&lt;/code&gt;, on the other hand, removes the irrelevant setup details. This allows them to determine more quickly what makes this test unique. They might not know immediately why it is failing, but at least they&#39;ll know why this test exists, and how it is different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Optimize for the reader, not the author&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chekhov&#39;s Gun is all about optimization of information. Anton Chekhov wants your writing to be as efficient as possible - so that readers can consume it with minimal effort and distraction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we&#39;re writing code, we are communicating with our teammates as much as we are communicating with the compiler. We are authors, and they are our readers. If we write our code in a way that optimizes for our writing experience, our readers will struggle. It won&#39;t take long for them to throw their hands up and say &amp;quot;let&#39;s do a rewrite, because I don&#39;t understand this.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we write our code in a way that optimizes for the reading experience, our readers will thank us. With less cognitive load from trying to decipher our code, they&#39;ll be able to focus on implementing their changes. Tests that minimize irrelevant setup are one simple way we can help the reader. Optimizing your code for the reader will help you build a more maintainable codebase.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>I&#39;m going to be busy</title>
		<link href="/blog/2017/04/im-going-to-be-busy/"/>
		<updated>2017-04-19T07:00:00-05:00</updated>
		<id>/blog/2017/04/im-going-to-be-busy/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year, I decided to become more involved in speaking at local meetups and events. In 2016 I got the speaking bug, but struggled a little to get into conferences. For 2017, I thought a good way to get experience was to engage at the local level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I scheduled a few meetup dates. Those events have gone really well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I submitted a good amount of abstracts to local and regional conferences, hoping to get into one or two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;And then I got into more than one or two&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started to get accepted to speak at conferences way more quickly than I expected. In 2016, my issue with conference submissions was that I couldn&#39;t get in. In 2017, my issue is the opposite. I have actually started retracting submissions from conferences, for fear of getting accepted and not having any time for my family and my training. A lucky problem to have!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My upcoming schedule&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Chicago Code Camp&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;April 29, Chicago&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ll be presenting my &amp;quot;Getting Started With React&amp;quot; talk at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chicagocodecamp.com/&quot;&gt;Chicago Code Camp&lt;/a&gt; at the end of April.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing that is interesting about speaking is that you never really know what talks will get picked up. My &amp;quot;Getting Started With React&amp;quot; talk was never really intended to happen - it came out of a workshop I did for our internship program at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.centare.com&quot;&gt;Centare&lt;/a&gt;, and I was reluctant to submit it anywhere. But after Chicago Code Camp, I will have given this talk more than any other talk. Crazy how that works out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Self.conference&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;May 19-20, Detroit&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will be doing my favorite talk - &amp;quot;Code Is Communication&amp;quot; - at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.selfconference.org&quot;&gt;Self.conference&lt;/a&gt; in May.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a really fun talk, and I&#39;m excited to get to do it again. I&#39;m also really excited about the other talks at this conference. Getting accepted to Self.conference was my first big surprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Open Source North&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;June 8, Twin Cities&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In June, I&#39;ll be doing a revamp of my oldest talk - &amp;quot;The Static Web Revolution&amp;quot; - at &lt;a href=&quot;http://opensourcenorth.com&quot;&gt;Open Source North&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m excited about some visual updates I&#39;ll be making for the slides for this talk, playing on the &amp;quot;revolution&amp;quot; idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;That Conference&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;August 7-9, Wisconsin Dells&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh man, this is the grandaddy of them all. This conference (that conference) is the reason I wanted to start speaking. I saw Cory House speak two years ago, and realized this was what I wanted to do. Getting into &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thatconference.com&quot;&gt;That Conference&lt;/a&gt; was the first speaking goal I set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yeah, I&#39;m pretty stoked about this one. I&#39;ll be doing &amp;quot;The Static Web revolution&amp;quot; here as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Midwest JS&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;August 16-18, Twin Cities&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to the Twin Cities again, this time for &lt;a href=&quot;http://midwestjs.com/&quot;&gt;Midwest JS&lt;/a&gt;. I&#39;d heard great things about this conference in 2016, so I was planning on attending even if I hadn&#39;t gotten in as a speaker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ll be doing a brand new talk here - &amp;quot;Unit Testing Your React App&amp;quot;. This talk was born out of the work I&#39;ve been doing over the last year or so, as well as a desire to learn more about Jest and Enzyme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Lessons Learned&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few things I&#39;ve learned from this year of craziness, so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Keep submitting.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was frustrated last year, and early this year, with not getting accepted into conferences. Admittedly, some of my very early submissions were not very good. But I thought a lot of the stuff I was submitting last year and early this year was pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out it was, because all of the talks I had picked up this year were things that had been submitted and rejected many times. Especially early on, I think the ratio of rejected to accepted is at least 5 to 1. I just knew I wanted to speak at conferences, so I pushed through the rejection, and it is paying off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;You never know which talks will be accepted.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It blows my mind how many times I&#39;ll be giving my intro to React talk. I hesitated to submit that talk every single time. I thought &amp;quot;this is such a basic thing, they must get a ton of these, why would mine get picked?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not sure why. But it did, several times. So, yeah - you never know which talks are interesting to organizers. It might be the one you least expect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Don&#39;t spread yourself too thin.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For as many talks as I&#39;ll be doing this summer, I&#39;ve been pretty lucky with which ones have been selected. Considering the range of talks I&#39;d submitted to these events, I could have found myself with a brand new talk for every event. Luckily, I didn&#39;t, so I get to focus on nailing down just a few of them. And I only have one brand new one that I have to start from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For next year, I&#39;m going to make sure that I&#39;m submitting talks that I have a pretty good start on. I don&#39;t want to get stuck having to write 5 new talks over the summer. This can be a hard thing to balance when you&#39;re first starting - I just wanted to get into conferences, so I was submitting anything I thought was a good idea. But it probably makes sense to restrain those ideas a little, to make sure you don&#39;t get swamped with accepted talks that you haven&#39;t written.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Mocking ES2015 modules</title>
		<link href="/blog/2017/01/mocking-es2015-modules/"/>
		<updated>2017-01-05T06:00:00-06:00</updated>
		<id>/blog/2017/01/mocking-es2015-modules/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re unit testing code that is using ES2015 modules [&lt;a href=&quot;#footnotes&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;], you&#39;ll probably point want to mock dependencies at some point. For the most part this is just like mocking things in any code. My tool of choice right now is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jupiter/simple-mock&quot;&gt;simple-mock&lt;/a&gt;, but there are gajillions of options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Test-induced damage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is some test-induced damage that my team has come to accept with simple-mock, and I am guessing it would be an issue with other mocking libraries like it. While simple-mock is great for mocking functions that are properties on exported objects, it seemed difficult to mock standalone/named exported functions from dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we found this to be easy: [&lt;a href=&quot;#footnotes&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;//dependency.js
export default {
    someAction: function() {
        //....
    },
};

//test.js
import simple from &amp;quot;simple-mock&amp;quot;;

import dependency from &amp;quot;./dependency&amp;quot;;

describe(&amp;quot;feature&amp;quot;, function() {
    afterEach(function() {
        simple.restore();
    });

    it(&amp;quot;calls a dependency&amp;quot;, function() {
        //Arrange
        simple.mock(dependency, &amp;quot;someAction&amp;quot;);

        //Act
        systemUnderTest.execute();

        //Assert
        expect(dependency.someAction.callCount).to.equal(1);
    });
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the &lt;code&gt;simple.mock&lt;/code&gt; function is looking for an object, and a property on that object. So we found this to be difficult:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;//dependency.js
export function someAction() {
    //....
}

//test.js
import simple from &amp;quot;simple-mock&amp;quot;;

// Notice the difference in how we are importing...
import { someAction } from &amp;quot;./dependency&amp;quot;;

describe(&amp;quot;feature&amp;quot;, function() {
    afterEach(function() {
        simple.restore();
    });

    it(&amp;quot;calls a dependency&amp;quot;, function() {
        //Arrange
        // ¯\_(ツ)_/¯
        // How would we mock &#39;someAction&#39;? It isn&#39;t a property on an object.

        //Act
        systemUnderTest.execute();

        //Assert
        expect(someAction.callCount).to.equal(1);
    });
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result of our inability to solve this problem, we had accepted that we would always export a default object from our code, with functions on it as properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So while we wanted to export something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;//dependency.js - the desired way
export function someAction() {
    //....
}

export function otherAction() {
    //...
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We just always accepted that we would do this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;//dependency.js - the undesired way
export default {
    someAction: function() {
        //....
    },
    otherAction: function() {
        //...
    },
};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why does it matter?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s a reason this was not ideal. Modern bundlers are able to remove the unused exports out of your code, to reduce your bundle size. But code is only removed if it isn&#39;t imported. By exporting a single object with a bunch of functions on it, the entire object must be imported by the calling code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in the first example, if your code called &lt;code&gt;someAction&lt;/code&gt; but not &lt;code&gt;otherAction&lt;/code&gt;, your final bundle would only include &lt;code&gt;someAction&lt;/code&gt;. But in the second example, even if you are only ever calling &lt;code&gt;someAction&lt;/code&gt;...you are importing the entire object, and therefore the unused &lt;code&gt;otherAction&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our app, that ends up not being a problem, because we are using all of the code we write. But if we were writing a library, or some code that was intended to be shared by other apps and therefore might not use everything, this would not be cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;But there is a better way to import the dependency.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, we discovered the answer to our problems. The &amp;quot;import * as&amp;quot; syntax allows you to import all exports from a dependency, expanding them onto an object - and therefore allowing you to mock a named/standalone function from your dependency. [&lt;a href=&quot;#footnotes&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So all that changes is how we import dependencies into our tests:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;//dependency.js
export function someAction() {
    //....
}

//test.js
import simple from &amp;quot;simple-mock&amp;quot;;

//     vvvvvvvvvvvvvvv Notice the difference in how we are importing
import * as dependency from &amp;quot;./dependency&amp;quot;;
//     ^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^

describe(&amp;quot;feature&amp;quot;, function() {
    afterEach(function() {
        simple.restore();
    });

    it(&amp;quot;calls a dependency&amp;quot;, function() {
        //Arrange
        // and now we can pass simple.mock a property on an object.
        simple.mock(dependency, &amp;quot;someAction&amp;quot;);

        //Act
        systemUnderTest.execute();

        //Assert
        expect(dependency.someAction.callCount).to.equal(1);
    });
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hooray, JavaScript! Hooray, mocking! Boo, test-induced damage!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] If you aren&#39;t unit testing your JS, you should be! It is not as scary as it sounds. You&#39;ll see great improvements to the quality of your front-end code. As an added bonus, the guilt that you probably feel for not testing your JS will disappear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2]&lt;a href=&quot;http://mochajs.org/#arrow-functions&quot;&gt;why aren&#39;t you using es2015 arrow functions in your tests?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[3] I ain&#39;t gonna lie, the discovery of this functionality was, as usual, the result of a &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/a/38414160/1585069&quot;&gt;stackoverflow search&lt;/a&gt; that I definitely tried a long time ago, but must have narrowly missed.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>My 2016 recap</title>
		<link href="/blog/2017/01/my-2016-recap/"/>
		<updated>2017-01-03T06:00:00-06:00</updated>
		<id>/blog/2017/01/my-2016-recap/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;2016 was a ...year that happened. Love it or hate it, it happened. At a personal level, I had a pretty fantastic 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;I discovered what I want to do when I grow up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevermind that I am a few weeks from being able to say &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jXEde89WC44&quot;&gt;I&#39;m a man, I&#39;m 40!&lt;/a&gt; It was 2016 when I realized what it is I want to do with my career - I want to speak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was an intern at State Farm in the summer of 1998, I was forced to attend Toastmasters on a regular basis. I hated it. It seemed like a bunch of old people who liked to hear themselves talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I was not bad at it. One of our assigments was to give a speech about..well I&#39;m not sure what, actually....and in silent protest I gave my speech about all the ways I procrastinated writing it. It went over really well, and I was voted my group&#39;s finalist, which meant there was a chance I would have to give it in front of the entire group of interns. My instructor told me I was &amp;quot;quite a wordsmith&amp;quot; (+1 for vocabulary), but I could use some practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ended up not being picked to speak in the finals, which I was pretty excited about. I left that summer with a bad taste in my mouth for Toastmasters - though to be fair, I was young and hated everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I also left with the knowledge that I didn&#39;t hate the actual act of speaking. Throughout my career I&#39;ve been happy to speak to coworkers in internal lunch-and-learns. But until recently, I had never gone much further than that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In late 2015, having done a lunch-and-learn on TDD, my boss asked if I was interested in getting out and speaking outside of the company. My TDD lunch-and-learn was not great - lots of bullet points, and too much information crammed into tiny spaces. But I enjoyed it, so I said yes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in 2016, my goal was really to get out and speak. And when I did - I realized I love it. I love the amount of learning I do when I research a topic to death, because I don&#39;t want to look foolish. I love telling jokes that not everyone gets. I love telling stories that reframe technical ideas in terms of real life. And despite the 10 minutes of &amp;quot;oh crap this is really happening&amp;quot; I feel as the talk is about to start, I love the rush I feel 15 minutes into the talk when the audience is engaged, and laughing at my dumb jokes, and listening to my dumb stories about grocery shopping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;So I did some speaking in 2016&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spoke at Milwaukee meetups twice in 2016. Once on static site generation, and once on clean code, as a lightning talk. These were my first two times speaking outside of my job. The thing I noticed the most was that people were actually engaged and listening. I thought speaking in front of co-workers would have been easier, because they were people I know...but since so many people are just there to pass some time while they eat their lunch, the engagement level isn&#39;t very high. When you are speaking outside of work, you are speaking to people who actively sought out your talk - so the engagement level is way higher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also got lucky enough to get into four conferences/camps in 2016!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first conference speaking opportunity ever - &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2016/06/chicago-coder-conference&quot;&gt;at Chicago Coder Conference&lt;/a&gt; - was at a conference that I didn&#39;t know anyone on the selection committee. That felt pretty good. I did a variation of my static site generation talk. I met some great people, and had a really fun time in downtown Chicago for a couple days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later in the year, I spoke at &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2016/11/october-recap&quot;&gt;MKE DOT NET and Milwaukee Code Camp&lt;/a&gt;. Each time I&#39;ve spoken, it has gotten easier. At MKE DOT NET, I got a ton of great reviews in our follow-up survey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also got to speak at another Centare-run event in December - QA Camp. This was an event for QA professionals, and I tag-teamed a talk with my co-worker &lt;a href=&quot;http://thefoxgang.com/&quot;&gt;Tyler Evert&lt;/a&gt;, called &amp;quot;Tight Feedback Loops with TDD and DevOps.&amp;quot; This was my first tag-team talk, and it was really fun. Again, we got a ton of great reviews in the follow-up survey. I feel like I am on the right track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really wanted to get into That Conference in 2016, but it didn&#39;t happen. Looking back at the abstract I submitted, I am not surprised. It was wordy. I was crafting it as if the reader had nothing to do on a cold winter Saturday, poured themself a cup of coffee, kicked their feet up in front of the fireplace, and read my abstract.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;I got some great speaking advice at That Conference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably the best part of That Conference is the Open Spaces, in which anyone can propose any topic, and anyone can attend. I facilitated one on &amp;quot;becoming a tech speaker&amp;quot;, and it was amazing. I had tons of great speakers stop by to give advice and answer questions. It was in this session that I realized why I probably had my abstract rejected. I am still trying to figure out how to get my abstracts selected, I feel like it is a game that I just haven&#39;t figured out yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the other great things I learned about speaking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&#39;s okay to reach out to organizers for feedback on why your abstracts weren&#39;t selected. I have used this advice several times already, and no one so far has declined my request for more info.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have backups for everything! This was a theme for me this year. At Milwaukee Code Camp, I thought I had accounted for everything...until the projector stopped working. At MKE DOT NET, Scott Hanselman worked with us to make sure we had backups of everything, including a projector...but we somehow missed a backup microphone, so obviously that&#39;s the one thing that started to die five minutes in. At QA Camp, the batteries in Tyler&#39;s clicker died halfway through. So yeah....backups for everything.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a checklist of all the things you want to verify during the setup of your talk. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.evernote.com/shard/s8/sh/bceb64d8-717f-4027-aaaa-6cd73d071ffc/be44ae852ddc8208&quot;&gt;Cory House&lt;/a&gt; has a very thorough example. This is incredibly helpful in those ten minutes before you start up, when your brain is freaking out a little bit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find what works for you. You will get advice from everyone about how to get started speaking, or get better at speaking. It turns out...you and that person may not agree on what makes a good speaker. Or you may learn differently than they do. Much like the adage about the most effective gym workout being the one that you will not quit - the best speaking tips are the ones that work for you. Which reminds me....&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;I stopped hating Markdown&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As early as a few months ago, I despised Markdown. It was too cryptic for me. But I realized that a weird combination of PowerPoint and OneNote weren&#39;t really working for me, for developing talks. I discovered that there were plenty of web-based alternatives, which would allow me to write my notes as an outline from the start, and iteratively build them up. The feedback I got from other speaking coworkers was that they sucked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I settled on &lt;a href=&quot;https://remarkjs.com&quot;&gt;RemarkJS&lt;/a&gt; and tried it anyway, and it completely works for me. I have written several talks with it, and will continue to write my talks that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like always, different strokes for different folks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, I&#39;ve now written talk outlines in Markdown enough times that I don&#39;t need a cheatsheet to do everything. Me from three months ago would not have believed this would happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Looking Forward to 2017&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am really happy with my career right now. I am submitting to conference CFP&#39;s any time I can. I am not being accepted a bunch -- yet. I love that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.centare.com&quot;&gt;Centare&lt;/a&gt; is giving me a ton of opportunity to speak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2017 I plan to speak a bit more at local meetups. I have a talk scheduled in late January with the local ReactJS meetup group, and I think spreading my brand locally is a great way for me to get regional conferences to notice me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And speaking of brand, I know this is something I need to work on in 2017. I am a bad self-marketer, and I need to get better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am also hoping to get into several regional conferences this year. I&#39;m submitting like crazy. It&#39;s not happening as quickly as I want it to, but I know this is what I want to do, so I&#39;m going to keep submitting.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>SSIS Is Annoying</title>
		<link href="/blog/2016/12/ssis-is-annoying/"/>
		<updated>2016-12-01T06:00:00-06:00</updated>
		<id>/blog/2016/12/ssis-is-annoying/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The project I&#39;m currently working on requires a spreadsheet to be imported into the database. SSIS seemed like the logical solution to this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But one month after dealing with SSIS, I am done with it. SSIS is like 85% awesome - but 15% &amp;quot;OMG I hate you&amp;quot;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QfzDUpB88x4&amp;amp;t=0m24s&quot;&gt;I wrote a song about it, like to hear it here it goes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;SSIS doesn&#39;t work consistently across machines&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of the package we are building is that it takes an Excel spreadsheet, sanitizes the data, and upserts it into a database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the data was a little bit long. We built some columns to handle 512 characters in the database. Everything seemed like it was working fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then one of the team members said it was failing for him, complaining about having to truncate data. We were all using the same spreadsheet, so this didn&#39;t make sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some investigation, it turns out all of the columns coming from the spreadsheet were capped at 255 characters. That is strange in itself, but we&#39;ll get to that. But why was it not failing for me?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still don&#39;t know the answer. Because everything in the package said that any value over 255 characters long should have been failing with an error. And that&#39;s what it was doing for my coworker - but not for me!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My bigger concern was this 255 character limit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;SSIS and Excel are just the worst&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SSIS thinks it is soooo smart. It can predict the widths of your columns for you, so you don&#39;t have to define them! Hooray!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except it only predicts the widths based on the first 8 rows of data. And if there is nothing very long in a column, it will set its max length to 255.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This wouldn&#39;t be the worst thing, if you could change the columns it got wrong. But you can&#39;t! You can try...but it will just blow away your changes when it re-samples the spreadsheet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;But you can change the default sample size from 8 rows to something else!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Um...&lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/a/8629065/1585069&quot;&gt;in your registry&lt;/a&gt;. That&#39;s a super fun way to make things fail differently for you than the rest of your team! And not a solution I plan on ever using.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Hey, didn&#39;t you read the rest of that answer? You can put a dummy row with long values in it, to trick SSIS!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yup, you can. Then you have to alter your package to ignore it...and hope that no one accidentally deletes that row one day. This is the least bad option...but still bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One side-effect of adding the dummy row is that now every column that is more than 255 characters long goes from a &lt;code&gt;DT_WSTR(255)&lt;/code&gt; type to a &lt;code&gt;DT_NTEXT&lt;/code&gt; type. That makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;But SSIS is bad at determining the length of text&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For all of those columns that were fine as a &lt;code&gt;DT_WSTR(255)&lt;/code&gt; type, the &lt;code&gt;LEN(x)&lt;/code&gt; function is gravy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for all of those columns that became &lt;code&gt;DT_NTEXT&lt;/code&gt;, SSIS will suddenly start doubling the column lengths. After the crazy pills wear off, you might find &lt;a href=&quot;https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms141797(v=sql.130).aspx&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the argument passed to the LEN function has a Binary Large Object Block (BLOB) data type, such as DT_TEXT, DT_NTEXT, or DT_IMAGE, the function returns a byte count.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ugh. I could see the argument for that with &lt;code&gt;DT_IMAGE&lt;/code&gt;. But &lt;code&gt;DT_TEXT&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;DT_NTEXT&lt;/code&gt;? They have &amp;quot;text&amp;quot; in the name! Why wouldn&#39;t I want the length of the text?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out you have to do the conversion yourself. &lt;code&gt;LEN( (DT_WSTR, 600) X)&lt;/code&gt; Thanks, SSIS!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;SSIS sucks for other reasons, too&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deployment is bad. Our timebox ended before we could figure out if we could run this all off of a server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It crashes often - at least with Visual Studio 2015. Especially when you pull latest on the repo and it has to reload the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it crashes, it leaves a process running (SSIS Debug Host) that you have to kill before you can run it again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can only have one Data Flow task open at one time. This is incredibly frustrating when you want to &amp;quot;copy&amp;quot; functionality across tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SSIS, consider me unimpressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My advice for someone who needs to import data from a spreadsheet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build a command-line project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have that command-line project use SqlBulkCopy to move all excel rows into a working table in your database.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have that command-line project then execute a bunch of T-SQL that does all your ETL things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hug yourself for avoiding SSIS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>October Recap</title>
		<link href="/blog/2016/11/october-recap/"/>
		<updated>2016-11-12T06:00:00-06:00</updated>
		<id>/blog/2016/11/october-recap/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;October was a crazy month! Aside from being peak soccer season for my kids, I spoke at Milwaukee Code Camp on the 15th, and MKE DOT NET at the end of the month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off, thanks to everyone who attended my sessions! I had a great time. I really enjoy the storytelling part of speaking. It is quickly becoming clear to me that stories are how you draw people in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Milwaukee Code Camp&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Milwaukee Code Camp, I presented my static site/JAM stack talk, in the &amp;quot;Backends? Where we&#39;re going we don&#39;t need...backends...&amp;quot; iteration. This talk has undergone constant revision since I first gave it, as I&#39;ve been learning how to do technical speaking. It will change before the next time, too. I had some great feedback from people, and I also noticed some things on my own that I am looking forward to improving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I battled some issues with the projector right as my talk was about to start. While I was waiting for help to arrive, I decided that I could get started without slides - and realized before help arrived that I could probably do this talk entirely without a projector. This was an encouraging feeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;MKE DOT NET&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Milwaukee Code Camp, the crazy ramped even higher. Aside from speaking at MKE DOT NET, I was also fairly involved in helping organize the conference. The end of October was a crazy busy time. Thankfully, I work with a ton of really great people who volunteered to make the event run silky smooth, given some scheduling challenges from the venue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My talk at MKE DOT NET almost couldn&#39;t have gone better. I had a great crowd, including some old friends. Everyone seemed really engaged - at one point I wanted to take a picture of literally the entire crowd looking up at a code sample, but the moment had passed by the time I got my phone out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slides for this talk can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://steven-j-hicks-speaking.netlify.com/code-is-communication/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One experiment from this talk that went really well was the use of a JavaScript-based presentation framework, instead of PowerPoint. I find that I spend a lot of time moving things around in PowerPoint, and I really wanted something where I could use CSS to keep my slides consistent. I also wanted to be able to keep my slides in a git repo. I did a little research and found that &lt;a href=&quot;https://remarkjs.com&quot;&gt;remark&lt;/a&gt; most closely met the vision in my head.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It worked great! My plan moving forward is to use remark to build all my decks. I am not the biggest fan of markdown but I love being able to outline my talk in code, and build it out from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of great conversations I got out of these two events, but right up near the top was an opportunity to work with Scott Hanselman to prepare the A/V equipment for his keynote. I got some great tips from him on speaking, as well as making MKE DOT NET more diverse next year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/mkedotnet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Steven Hicks and Scott Hanselman&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Up Next&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My next scheduled talk will be at QA Camp in Milwaukee, on December 8th. I&#39;ll be speaking with a colleague on tightening the feedback loop with TDD and DevOps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve also got a couple proposals that I&#39;m awaiting responses from, and I&#39;m looking forward to submitting to as many CFPs as I can in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Getting Started With TDD</title>
		<link href="/blog/2016/08/getting-started-with-tdd/"/>
		<updated>2016-08-19T07:00:00-05:00</updated>
		<id>/blog/2016/08/getting-started-with-tdd/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, a coworker asked me to send him some good resources for introducing a team to TDD. Rather than hoarding the info, this seemed like something I should probably put somewhere for the next person that asks. Much of this is information that I talked about in my &amp;quot;You down with TDD? Yeah you know me&amp;quot; talk that I wish I could give more often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is entirely too much information to fit into one place, so I&#39;ve broken the info down a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2016/08/my-tdd-sales-pitch&quot;&gt;My TDD sales pitch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2016/08/getting-started-with-tdd&quot;&gt;Getting started with TDD (this post!)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Getting Started&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right, so there are a couple different ways to handle this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Cold Turkey&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many who will say that cold turkey is the way to go to learn TDD. TDD all the things, on all the projects, all the time! The only way to truly learn it is to be thrown into the fire, with no way to escape but a fireman&#39;s axe labelled &amp;quot;TDD&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe this works for you. If it does...I apologize, I don&#39;t have any advice, because this would never work for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Baby Steps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things generally work better for me if I dip my toes in the water first. TDD for me took a couple years of biting off a little more each time. It went something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consume resources&lt;/strong&gt;. Watch videos. Read blogs. Learn what TDD is all about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practice.&lt;/strong&gt; Start messing around with some meaningless code, just to see what TDD feels like. &lt;a href=&quot;http://codekata.com/&quot;&gt;Code katas&lt;/a&gt; are a great medium for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduce TDD into one project, in one feature.&lt;/strong&gt; Sometimes there is a task on a project that just feels perfectly made for TDD. Something where you need to do some calculations, for example. The test scenarios practically write themselves. It is here that you can start to introduce TDD into your development flow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the features will end up being more difficult to TDD than you expected - that&#39;s okay. If you need to stop, you can stop. You also might find yourself feeling like you are taking to long to get things done, the TDD learning curve is just fighting you. Again - I stopped here many times myself, and abandoned TDD until I felt like I was back on schedule. &lt;strong&gt;It&#39;s okay to introduce the practice a little bit at a time.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduce TDD into one project, in many features.&lt;/strong&gt; Alright, so now you&#39;re starting to build momentum and confidence. Start TDD&#39;ing more!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TDD all the things!&lt;/strong&gt; Okay, not really. There are things that are just not worth testing or TDD&#39;ing, in my opinion. The cost is just too high for the value you get. But now you can go into a project saying &amp;quot;yeah, we&#39;re going to TDD the snot out of this thing.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The man himself&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there&#39;s anyone who knows anything about TDD, it&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/KentBeck&quot;&gt;Kent Beck&lt;/a&gt;. These resources would be a good place to start if you would like to learn from &amp;quot;the source&amp;quot; of TDD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Test-Driven-Development-Kent-Beck/dp/0321146530/ref=sr_1_1&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;He wrote a book.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I would be lying if I said I read it but I would like to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pragprog.com/screencasts/v-kbtdd/test-driven-development&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;He made some videos.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I would be lying if I said I&#39;ve watched them but I would like to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Mark Seemann&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ll talk about this more in another post, but the most significant way to improve your ability to TDD is to improve your ability to write tests. &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.ploeh.dk/about/&quot;&gt;Mark Seemann&lt;/a&gt; is full of good tips on writing autonomous tests that follow principles of clean software design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://app.pluralsight.com/library/courses/advanced-unit-testing/table-of-contents&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;He has a really good Pluralsight video on Advanced Unit Testing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I have watched this and it has significantly improved my test code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://app.pluralsight.com/library/courses/outside-in-tdd/table-of-contents&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;He has another Pluralsight video called Outside-In TDD.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I have not watched this but I want to. There are a couple strategies to TDD - outside-in, and then I guess obviously inside-out. Inside-out seems to be more natural for people new to TDD. You build the inner-most components (i.e. data-access) first, then work your way out. Outside-in is, in my opinion, the correct way to TDD. Build the outer-most component (i.e. the UI) first, then work your way in. The big advantage to outside-in is that it allows you to shape the interfaces between components as the caller would want to use them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Chess TDD series&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would be lying if I said I watched all 60-some episodes, but Erik Dietrich put together a really nice &lt;a href=&quot;href=&#39;http://www.daedtech.com/tag/chesstdd/&#39;&quot;&gt;series of screencasts&lt;/a&gt;, which captured him using TDD to build a chess game. It is neat to see it in action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A good testing checklist&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dzone.com/articles/unit-testing-checklist&quot;&gt;This is a checklist&lt;/a&gt; that helps you write good tests. Your tests are as important as your system code, so you should put effort into writing good, clean test code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;TDD is an investment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully the above resources can help you get started with TDD. Like any other skill, TDD takes practice and patience. It took me years to get from TDD newb to feeling totally comfortable with it, so don&#39;t feel discouraged if it feels difficult at first.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>My TDD Sales Pitch</title>
		<link href="/blog/2016/08/my-tdd-sales-pitch/"/>
		<updated>2016-08-18T07:00:00-05:00</updated>
		<id>/blog/2016/08/my-tdd-sales-pitch/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, a coworker asked me to send him some good resources for introducing a team to TDD. Rather than hoarding the info, this seemed like something I should probably put somewhere for the next person that asks. Much of this is information that I talked about in my &amp;quot;You down with TDD? Yeah you know me&amp;quot; talk that I wish I could give more often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is entirely too much information to fit into one place, so I&#39;ve broken the info down a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2016/08/my-tdd-sales-pitch&quot;&gt;My TDD sales pitch (this post!)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2016/08/getting-started-with-tdd&quot;&gt;Getting started with TDD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Intro to TDD&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test-driven_development&quot;&gt;the wikipedia article&lt;/a&gt; has a good summary of what TDD is. A summary -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Every system change that you make requires a failing test first.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is often boiled down to the slogan &lt;strong&gt;&amp;quot;Red/Green/Refactor&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt;. Red = write a failing test, Green = make the test pass by writing &amp;quot;just enough&amp;quot; code, and Refactor &amp;quot;just enough&amp;quot; that you are happy with the result.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TDD encourages simplicity.&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;quot;Just enough&amp;quot; is in that last bullet point twice. TDD wants to prevent you from over-designing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TDD is a discipline.&lt;/strong&gt; It is not easy to learn, and it is easy to fall out of habit. It takes practice. I worked on incorporating TDD into my dev flow for probably 2 years before it finally stuck.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why use TDD?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the reasons I like TDD are found in the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TDD can lead to simpler designs.&lt;/strong&gt; Emphasis on &amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;strong&gt;CAN&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;. Not will. It is kind of a chicken vs egg situation - if you do TDD, your designs can be simpler...if you simplify your designs, it makes TDD easier. You can still do TDD with complex designs but that is often the type of scenario that causes a person to stop doing TDD.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TDD can lead to smaller units of code/looser coupling/cleaner interfaces.&lt;/strong&gt; Similar to the previous point, this is not a guaranteed result.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TDD can improve your code coverage.&lt;/strong&gt; You are writing tests before each line of system code - so you are usually getting pretty close to 100% coverage on anything you are using TDD for. I will not get into the discussion of whether 100% coverage is valuable....but if a high coverage number is important to you, TDD can help.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favorite reasons that I like TDD are found beyond the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TDD questions your understandings of the requirements.&lt;/strong&gt; The moment in TDD when you are deciding what tests to write for your component is a great moment to reflect on what you do and don&#39;t know about the system. It is also a great moment for you and your team to talk, to figure out how to handle the things you don&#39;t know about the system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TDD documents the requirements.&lt;/strong&gt; TDD gives you thorough tests, which tell the next person looking at the code what you expected the system to do. They are also great for when a Quality Engineer asks you what should happen in a specific scenario, and you can&#39;t exactly remember.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TDD is a good guide for code reviews.&lt;/strong&gt; Without TDD, code reviews that I&#39;ve done are generally aimless and we end up meandering through the code. When I am using TDD to write something, I start with the tests to guide me through the code review. We can talk about all the things that were and weren&#39;t covered by my changes easily, by following the tests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TDD gives you confidence&lt;/strong&gt; that your code works as you expected it to. If I make a change, I know I will have a broken test telling me if an unintended side-effect occurred.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TDD reduces mental clutter.&lt;/strong&gt; This is my favorite. When my wife sends me to the store for a couple things, there is like a 90% chance that I will screw it up. If I&#39;m supposed to get milk, eggs, and butter, I will come home with milk, eggs, bacon, and beer....but no butter. My brain can&#39;t be trusted to remember a list of three groceries. It &lt;strong&gt;definitely&lt;/strong&gt; can&#39;t be trusted to remember hundreds of different test scenarios for the code I&#39;m working on. TDD gets me the confidence to know when I broke something that I didn&#39;t think I would break, rather than having to fumble manually through some scenarios that I half remember.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why not use TDD?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are lots of arguments people, including myself, have made to not use TDD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It is hard.&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah...at first. Like any skill, it takes practice, and eventually it becomes easier. The benefits outweigh the learning curve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It is slow.&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah...at first. Again, you eventually get faster. Plus, bugs are generally easier to figure out because you&#39;re writing simpler code, so you spend way less time in a debugger.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have tried and &lt;strong&gt;my tests were just breaking any time I wanted to change anything&lt;/strong&gt;. Again, you get better at this over time, too. When I started out, my tests were big. They had a lot of setup, and a lot of assertions...because I wasn&#39;t writing very small units. Over time, you learn to write smaller units of code, which require less test setup. When small tests for small units of code break, they are easier to fix, so it&#39;s not that big of a deal that you broke a test.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I don&#39;t need all that test coverage.&lt;/strong&gt; Maybe. I agree that 100% coverage is unreasonable. There definitely seems to be diminishing returns after about 80%. But sometimes I think we convince ourselves that we don&#39;t need coverage on something because we just aren&#39;t sure how to test it. As you get better at writing simpler units of code, it&#39;s hard to convince yourself not to cover stuff, because it&#39;s a lot easier than it used to be.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I test after.&lt;/strong&gt; First off, good for you. I know I have a tendency to pass on testing if I am doing it after, and I suspect you may be similar. Also - when you&#39;re testing after, it is often at a point in the current sprint/iteration/whatever that you don&#39;t really want to be making changes to the underlying code, because you don&#39;t want to break anything that&#39;s already been tested. So you write your tests around what is easy to test. Or #yolo, you refactor the code to be more testable, and don&#39;t tell anyone you made the changes, because there&#39;s no time to test them. (Guilty.) In either case....wouldn&#39;t it be cool if you could refactor while covered by tests, instead of refactoring to write tests?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All that stuff &lt;a href=&quot;http://david.heinemeierhansson.com/2014/tdd-is-dead-long-live-testing.html&quot;&gt;that DHH said&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. The phrase I have best heard to describe DHH&#39;s post is &amp;quot;test-induced damage&amp;quot;. Abstractions just for the sake of testing, for example. To me, I see it more as &amp;quot;test-induced compromise&amp;quot; than damage. I can write unit tests for all my things just by making a few small design changes? Sign me up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TDD is not a silver bullet.&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, it&#39;s not. Nothing is. But that doesn&#39;t mean it doesn&#39;t have value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s my sales pitch. Next up I&#39;ll list &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2016/08/getting-started-with-tdd&quot;&gt;a few good resources for getting started with TDD&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Back-ends? Where we&#39;re going, we don&#39;t need...back-ends.....</title>
		<link href="/blog/2016/06/chicago-coder-conference/"/>
		<updated>2016-06-10T07:00:00-05:00</updated>
		<id>/blog/2016/06/chicago-coder-conference/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I got to present at this year&#39;s Chicago Coder Conference, about static site generators and the &amp;quot;JAM stack.&amp;quot; This is a talk I&#39;ve been doing variations of here and there for about six months. It was the first time I&#39;ve been lucky enough to present at a conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a great time! I was a bit disheartened by the fact that I&#39;d been time-slotted up against Uncle Bob, and I even told everyone I met the first day of the conference that they should go listen to him instead of me. It was an honor to be speaking at the same venue as him, he is an amazing speaker and a role model for me. I just wish I hadn&#39;t had to compete with him for listeners....&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, I had about 15 people come hang out and listen to me. I had great conversation with several of them before and after my talk. I&#39;ve been going into these things with the thought that if I get two people to legitimately listen to what I have to say, and I can legitimately help them, it is a win. In this case, I think I definitely met that goal, and I am pretty hungry to speak again soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As much as I hate taking selfies, I did convince myself to take one on my way out of town. The squatty looking building in the background, the Gleacher Center, is where I spoke.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/chicagocoderconf.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Steven Hicks at Chicago Coder Conference&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Maybe I was wrong about React</title>
		<link href="/blog/2016/04/maybe-i-was-wrong-about-react/"/>
		<updated>2016-04-07T07:00:00-05:00</updated>
		<id>/blog/2016/04/maybe-i-was-wrong-about-react/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;So many places to start&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of examples of how to set up a project with React, and very little direction on the best route. The first time I tried to do this, I ended up with a whole lot of analysis paralysis, and couldn&#39;t figure out where to even start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;It depends on how you learn&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of the advice you get on how to learn React and its ecosystem is to learn each individual piece, one thing at a time. Definitely DO NOT start with a &amp;quot;starter kit&amp;quot;, they say. That isn&#39;t going to teach you anything, they say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But suddenly in retrospect I&#39;m realizing, that is why I struggled so much the first time I tried to learn React. I am not that kind of learner. I am a &amp;quot;give me a real live working example and I will tweak things until they break and learn from all the mistakes I make&amp;quot; kind of learner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what is the best way to fire up a working example of something? Yeoman. Find a generator that fits your tech stack, and start there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Yo let&#39;s do this&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So off to &lt;a href=&quot;http://yeoman.io/generators&quot;&gt;yeoman.io/generators&lt;/a&gt; we go...where we search for &#39;react&#39;, and get....tons....and tons....of results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/yeoman-react.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Yeoman React search&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking through some of the results, I see one that has the things I&#39;m looking for - &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/stylesuxx/generator-react-webpack-redux&quot;&gt;react-webpack-redux&lt;/a&gt;, which is really an extension of another generator, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/newtriks/generator-react-webpack&quot;&gt;react-webpack&lt;/a&gt;. The things I want out of the box, and the things this generator offers out of the box, are...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Redux&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ES2015&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unit testing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sass or Less&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The moment of truth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So following the directions, we install the generator via npm, then generate a new site with yeoman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;yo react-webpack-redux&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After answering a few questions for setup, comes the moment of truth. If all goes according to plan, I should be able to just start the app with&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;pre npm start&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and HOLY CRAP I CAN AND IT JUST WORKS OH MY GEEZ HOW MUCH TIME DID I WASTE TRYING TO DO THIS THE LAST TIME!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/static/img/dancing_banana.gif&quot; style=&quot;width:200px&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The verdict - Oh my goodness this actually is kind of easy!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, jeez. This was so much easier than the first time I tried to set up a React project. I am very pleased. I am beyond very pleased. I am actually in complete disbelief and wish I had realized it could be this easy this the first time. This makes learning React a much more tolerable proposition.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Ember looks neat</title>
		<link href="/blog/2016/03/emberLooksNeat/"/>
		<updated>2016-03-24T07:00:00-05:00</updated>
		<id>/blog/2016/03/emberLooksNeat/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;I got 99 problems and 98 of them are javascript MV* frameworks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am in the market for a new MV* framework in Javascript. I&#39;ve done Angular 1, many times. There are things I like about it - dependency injection is easy, meaning unit testing is easy; there is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/johnpapa/angular-styleguide&quot;&gt;good guidance&lt;/a&gt; on style and best practices; documentation is pretty great. There are also things I don&#39;t like about it - it can be slow; the digest cycle can make me want to rip my hair out at times; writing directives can be confusing and sometimes feels a little like throwing darts at a dartboard to see what sticks. But that ship has sailed, and there are too many other frameworks to stick with Angular 1 for life. I am a breadth of knowledge guy, not depth of knowledge - and the longer I stick with one framework, the more I feel like I&#39;m falling behind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Angular 2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The logical framework for me is Angular 2, right? I have all that Angular 1 experience. They&#39;ve now provided good &lt;a href=&quot;https://angular.io/docs/ts/latest/guide/upgrade.html&quot;&gt;guidance on migration&lt;/a&gt;,which is way better than when it was announced, and we all thought we&#39;d be rewriting apps from scratch. But to be honest, I haven&#39;t looked into Angular 2 a whole lot, because when I look at the examples, the views look atrocious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;li *ngFor=&amp;quot;#hero of heroes&amp;quot; (click)=&amp;quot;onSelect(hero)&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;span class=&amp;quot;badge&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt; 
&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;some-component [prop]=&amp;quot;someExp&amp;quot; (event)=&amp;quot;someEvent()&amp;quot; [(twoWayProp)]=&amp;quot;someExp&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/show-title&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good gracious, look at all those symbols. Maybe I&#39;m being a crybaby, but I can&#39;t imagine myself staring at views like that all day without (a) needing a cheat-sheet to tell me which symbol to use when, and (b) throwing up. I despise Markdown for its use of semantic symbols; the symbols in Angular 2 seem just as confusing to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;That React, it&#39;s so hot right now!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, most of what I&#39;ve learned so far about React, I&#39;ve learned from &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@housecor&quot;&gt;Cory House&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pluralsight.com/courses/react-flux-building-applications&quot;&gt;his Pluralsight course&lt;/a&gt; is a great place to start. This dude is an amazing speaker, and I highly recommend checking him out if you get a chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really like a lot of things about React.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The virtualDom diffing is cool. Better performance is nothing to complain about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I like the concept of uni-directional flow. I&#39;ve played with both Flux and Redux, and before you get lawyery on me I know that&#39;s not technically part of React, but it is part of the ecosystem - and if you&#39;re going to build something with React, you&#39;re going to use either Flux or Redux because all of the examples do too. Flux is okay, but has too much boilerplate repetition for my tastes. Redux I find to be pretty neat - I like the &lt;a href=&quot;http://redux.js.org/docs/introduction/ThreePrinciples.html&quot;&gt;guiding principles&lt;/a&gt; - a single source of truth, read-only state, and the use of pure functions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The language is simple, and it&#39;s pretty easy to figure out what&#39;s going on in a component.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jsx is awesome. I love the fact that you get a compile error when you typo something in a component - as opposed to something silently failing in most other frameworks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dislikes list is much shorter....but the one item on the list is huge. Javascript tools fatigue is a real thing, and React is the ultimate example of it. I hope you like to have opinions about everything - cuz you&#39;re gonna need to. Setting up a project in React is a painful experience. React embraces the micro-library culture of npm - so you need to pick your own libraries for pretty much everything. If you&#39;re the kind of person who wants control over every..single..feature when you buy a new car, then React is going to make you happy. I am not one of those people. I am pretty happy to have three packages to choose from. I don&#39;t want to fill out a form for two hours choosing between 2 cupholders and 3. I want a car, and I want to drive it, and I don&#39;t much care for the details. Getting up and running with React can be a challenge, and one that makes me not want to use React.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Ember&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which brings me to Ember. I don&#39;t know a whole lot about Ember. In fact, most of what I know, I learned from &lt;a href=&quot;http://hanselminutes.com/516/ambitious-ux-and-ambitious-apps-with-ember-and-lauren-tan&quot;&gt;one episode of HanselMinutes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I think I like the most about Ember is that it provides opinions for you. This is my biggest issue right now with JavaScript development - you need to have an opinion about everything. I am a breadth of knowledge guy, rather than depth of knowledge - as a result, I have more interest in learning the opinions prescribed by a framework than in forcing my own opinions onto a framework. I want my MV* framework to have opinions for me so that I can focus on building something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heck, &lt;a href=&quot;http://emberjs.com/&quot;&gt;the slogan on their site&lt;/a&gt; is &amp;quot;more productive out of the box&amp;quot;. That is a slogan I can get behind.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Static Site Generators Are The New WordPress</title>
		<link href="/blog/2016/03/staticgen/"/>
		<updated>2016-03-10T06:00:00-06:00</updated>
		<id>/blog/2016/03/staticgen/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Static Site Generators Are The New WordPress&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently presented at the MKE Web Pros meetup group, about static site generators, and how you can build stupid simple websites with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dynamic CMS like WordPress is no longer the defacto answer to the statement &amp;quot;I need a website&amp;quot;. Static site generation can easily handle the needs of simple sites with infrequently changing content. Services are becoming more prevalent for adding interactive functionality to an otherwise static site - for example, Disqus for comments. And in many cases, where services can&#39;t be dropped directly onto your static site, a little technical courage and some javascript can get you what you need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Statically generated sites are much more performant and secure than a site run on a dynamic CMS. There are fewer moving parts, and since your content is literally served as static html files, fewer ways your site can be attacked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would love to say static site generation is the answer for all sites. But it&#39;s not quite ready for your non-technical relative&#39;s site. Until content editing is more user-friendly, static site generation is probably only for your simplest sites or your most technical friends&#39; websites. As a general rule, if the content editor is not capable or ready to write content using a language like Markdown, static site generation might not be the answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news is, we&#39;re headed toward a future where even your non-technical relative can publish content on a statically generated site. Services like Contentful and CloudCannon and plugins like Netlify-CMS are pushing in that direction. I don&#39;t think we&#39;re too far from a future where your non-technical relative can edit content in a WYSIWYG editor, click a button, and push changes to their statically generated site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.staticgen.com&quot;&gt;staticgen.com&lt;/a&gt; to get started with static site generation. There are way too many generators for me to recommend &amp;quot;the perfect one&amp;quot;. It is up to you to determine which generator works best for your scenario. For me, the answer is either HarpJs or Metalsmith. For you, the answer could be anything. Find the static generator for you, and let&#39;s start moving the web to a more performant and less vulnerable place.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
</feed>